<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An useful tractate to further Christians of these dangerous and back-sliding times, in the practice of the most needful duty of prayer Wherein are discover'd the nature, necessity and successe of fervent prayer: many objections answered, several practical cases of conscience resolved; and all briefly applied from this text, viz. James 5. 16. The effectual fervent-prayer of a righteous man availeth much. Being the substance of several sermons preached in the town of Columpton in Devon. / By William Crompton M.A. minister of that part of Christs Church there.</title>
            <author>Crompton, William, 1599?-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 225 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80869</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2142_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210127</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868952</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868952</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121309</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80869)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121309)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 244:E2142[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An useful tractate to further Christians of these dangerous and back-sliding times, in the practice of the most needful duty of prayer Wherein are discover'd the nature, necessity and successe of fervent prayer: many objections answered, several practical cases of conscience resolved; and all briefly applied from this text, viz. James 5. 16. The effectual fervent-prayer of a righteous man availeth much. Being the substance of several sermons preached in the town of Columpton in Devon. / By William Crompton M.A. minister of that part of Christs Church there.</title>
                  <author>Crompton, William, 1599?-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 152 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for Philemon Stephens, at the Gilded Lion in S. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A treatise of prayer.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121309:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN USEFUL TRACTATE TO Further Chriſtians of theſe <hi>dangerous</hi> and <hi>back-ſliding</hi> times, in the <hi>Practice</hi> of the moſt needful Duty of PRAYER.</p>
            <p>Wherein are diſcover'd the nature, neceſſity and ſucceſſe of <hi>FERVENT PRAYER:</hi> Many <hi>Objections</hi> anſwered, ſeveral Practical <hi>Caſes</hi> of Conſcience reſolved; and all briefly applied from this Text, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>James 5.16. </bibl>
               <hi>The effectual fervent-prayer of a righteous man availeth much.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Being the ſubſtance of ſeveral Sermons Preached in the Town of <hi>Columpton</hi> in <hi>Devon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Crompton M. A.</hi> Miniſter of that part of Chriſts Church there.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John 16.23.</hi>
                  </bibl> And in that day ye ſhall ask me nothing: Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, verily, I ſay unto you, Whatſoever ye ſhall ask in my name, he will give it you.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Coloſſ. 4.2.</hi>
                  </bibl> Continue in prayer, and watch in the ſame with thankſgiving.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens,</hi> at the Gilded <hi>Lion</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard. 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:121309:2"/>
            <p>ALthough there be many <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Treatiſes</hi> already printed concerning <hi>Prayer,</hi> yet this enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſe hath a <hi>peculiar excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency</hi> in it, for which it deſerves to be <hi>bought,</hi> and <hi>diligently peruſed.</hi> And let me aſſure the <hi>Reader,</hi> that he will neither repent of his <hi>mony,</hi> nor his <hi>pains;</hi> and that it will be his <hi>happineſſe</hi> to be transformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the doctrine herein delivered.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Febr.</hi> 15. 1658.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> EDM. CALAMY.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121309:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:121309:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have peruſed this <hi>Treatiſe of Prayer,</hi> from the beginning to the end; and I conceive it will be good ſervice to God and his Church in the making of it publick; not ſo much becauſe of the <hi>delight</hi> it will yield to thoſe that read it, as becauſe I hope the holy directions which are herein given, will be of much avail to teach men to pray ſo, that their prayers may be the <hi>Lords delight,</hi> Pro. <hi>15.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>ARTH. JACKSON, Paſtor of the Church of</hi> Faiths <hi>under</hi> Pauls.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Januar. <hi>19. 1658.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:121309:3"/>
            <head>TO THE VVORSHIPFUL ROBERT COCKRAM Eſquire, his honoured <hi>Patron;</hi> with the reſt of my conſtant Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours in the Town and Pariſh of <hi>Columpton, The</hi> dew of Heaven <hi>be your portion, as the beauty and fatneſſe of the earth is your habitation:</hi> grace, mercy and peace <hi>be upon the heads and hearts of you all,</hi> that love Chriſt Jeſus in ſincerity.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides my readineſſe to gratifie the deſire of ſome among you, and willingneſſe to give ſome ſignal of my <hi>unfeigned love</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:121309:4"/> to you all, I have been eaſily induced to publiſh the following <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> by theſe following con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That I might the better confirm <hi>theſe things wherein you have been inſtructed</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 1.4.</note>: and not ſeem to labour altogether in vain, by beſtowing ſo much time on that which was to vaniſh in the hearing: a ſad lot which waits on the beſt things committed to <hi>leak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ears,</hi> as water poured into a veſſel full of chinks.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That I might benefit thoſe abſent, yea if it may be, <hi>the people that are yet unborn,</hi> Pſal. 102.18.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That I might leave a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial with you, whenever it ſhall pleaſe the <hi>Lord of the Vineyard,</hi> whoſe I am, to call me off from you, and ſo ſupply my abſence,
<pb facs="tcp:121309:4"/> though by <hi>death,</hi> ſpeaking to you, when I cannot ſee you, yea li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with you, when dead and laid in the duſt<note n="†" place="margin">Sic Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaeus cum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaſſet Hebraeis &amp; ad gentes ire pararet, utile judicavit ſi iis quos corpore deſerebat, aliquid memoriale doctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae ſuae relinqueret. Ut Bel lib. <hi>4.</hi> de verb. Dei non ſcrip. c. <hi>4.</hi> notavit ex Euſebio.</note>.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe the matter thereof is weighty, and the deſigne of no <hi>ſmall</hi> conſequence: it is to guide you in your <hi>going</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> how to converſe with <hi>him,</hi> to manage well your performances; in which if you are defective, the whole will be unprofitable. Religion is curious <hi>clock work,</hi> if but one wheel fail, ſo w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll all the reſt: and as one ſtring in a <hi>Lute</hi> diſſonant and unharmonious to the reſt corrupteth the whole Muſick. There is in every duty abſolutely required righteouſneſſe <hi>quoad ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiam operis,</hi> and no leſſe <hi>quoad
<pb facs="tcp:121309:5"/> modum:</hi> the matter and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner are of equal concernment; <hi>the flie in the Apothecaries oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and miſcarriage in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians performance, render both unſavoury. If you are reſolved to the duty (as I hope you are, and more, <hi>Practitioners</hi> in it,) ſee here what it is will adorn your ſacrifice; why it muſt be ſo accommodated, and how it may be diſcerned: beſides other things which occur for your information therein.</p>
            <p>There are, its true, other more excellent Diſcourſes of this nature extant, ſome of the ſame metal bearing a better ſtamp: but this I commend to you ſooneſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your own, it is hony that was gathered for your uſe, milk drawn from your own breſt, and therefore moſt proper for you; it is a ſheaf gathered out of your
<pb facs="tcp:121309:5"/> own field: a diſh taken from your own table, if it be not ſo well filled as might be expected, ſo circumſtantiated as the <hi>ſubject</hi> doth deſerve, you cannot deſpiſe it, except you blame your ſelves who choſe the Cook.</p>
            <p>Accept it then with the ſame love it is offered: read it with the ſame diligence you heard it. If any among you may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, convinced, confirmed, reſolved, comforted, quickned, by any thing here preſented, I ſhall account a ſufficient recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and <hi>rejoice</hi> that I <hi>have not run in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, my <hi>Beloved,</hi> ſince I have opportunity, ſuffer me in the eye of the world to exhort you. The publiſhing of theſe things was chiefly intended for you, let it be <hi>your</hi> care, to be
<pb facs="tcp:121309:6"/> the principal Proficients by it; here is a talent committed to your careful improvement, lay it not in a <hi>napkin,</hi> hide it not in the earth. Now be doing; move (Planet-like) uniformly; Covet grace rather then gifts, as to pray more <hi>fervently,</hi> though leſſe notionally; yet ſtrive to come behinde in no ſpiritual gift. Be men of <hi>excellent ſpirits:</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe ſincerity by your <hi>fervent</hi> endeavours after communion with God and <hi>fellowſhip with Chriſt.</hi> Like the Eagle, ſoar aloft, but out of love to Heaven. Trade for grace, your <hi>trading</hi> on earth is ſlack, unprofitable. Let your converſation be now, where you would have it to be ſhortly, when you ſhall be here no more; be not ſlack in cloſet-ſervices; do not you <hi>as others that reſtrain prayer before God,</hi> but <hi>continue in prayer and watch in the ſame with
<pb facs="tcp:121309:6"/> thankſgiving; O pray continually,</hi> and that not out of <hi>form,</hi> but feeling. Serve God faithfully; keep cloſe to <hi>Christ</hi> your Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: Stand in your order, (O 'tis a ſtragling age!) fly not from your colours! quit your ſelves like men, and men of valour, ſouldiers in the <hi>ſpiritual war</hi> for Chriſt and <hi>his</hi> truth; manifeſt your actual memberſhip of the <hi>Militant</hi> Church, be mindeful of the yet ſuffering <hi>body of Chriſt;</hi> join your mutual forces for her help: <hi>fervent prayer</hi> will do it; be not weary nor wanting. But my-thinks I hear you reply, and ſay with <hi>Samuel, God forbid that we ſhould ſinne againſt the Lord in ceaſing to pray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will therefore diſmiſſe you with prayer to God for you, in the words of old <hi>Eli, Go in peace, and the Lord of Iſrael grant you your Petitions,</hi> which you have,
<pb facs="tcp:121309:7"/> or ſhall <hi>ſo</hi> ask of him for your ſelves or others! To his <hi>Grace</hi> I leave you, and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt affectionate Paſtor, Devoted to the ſervice of your faith.</hi> W. Crompton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:121309:7"/>
            <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> FORD'S <hi>PREFACE</hi> TOUCHING The enſuing Treatiſe, and the Subject thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Need not commend the Subject of this Diſcourſe to any that confeſſes there is a God. He that hath but ſo much Divinity, as to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a Deity, muſt needs grant Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be a neceſſary duty. For the uſefulneſſe I appeal to all that have found the benefit of it by experience: And they are ſuch as count of no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment, but what is the fruit, and return of prayers. It may be truly ſaid of Prayer; It is not more our duty,
<pb facs="tcp:121309:8"/> then our priviledge. Tis (as one ſaith) <hi>piae mentis cum Deo collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium,</hi> The converſe, and commerce that a gracious ſoul on earth hath with God in Heaven. A priviledge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as great as we are here capable of, that we may come to God as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to a father, and ſpeak to him, as a man ſpeaketh to his friend.</p>
            <p>Now he that hath but ſo much lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and patience as will give him leave to peruſe this ſhort Diſcourſe, will finde many encouragements to preſſe the performance of this duty, and many helps to direct him in it. Its aim and ſcope is nothing elſe but to teach us to pray. It meddles with no controverſie, only reſoves a Caſe or two in order to practice; the deſign of it being only to learn us how to reaſon the caſe, and plead our cauſe with God. In one word; It ſhews nothing but the practice of Religion in one great and neceſſary part of it. And if thoſe who pretend moſt to godlineſs would
<pb facs="tcp:121309:8"/> fall cloſer to their work in the practice, and think more of expreſsing the life, and power of it in <hi>effectual-fervent-prayer,</hi> &amp; the duties of perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal relations, and particular callings, I am ſure they ſhould finde more ſound peace and comfort, then now they do in many frivolous controverſies, and perverſe diſputings. For fooliſh queſtions do but puff men up in pride, and ſelf-conceitedneſſe: whereas <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual-fervent-prayer,</hi> and practical godlineſſe edifie, and establiſh in grace, render men approved to God, and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the ſight of all that have to do with them. Tis very remarkable what the reverend Authour obſerves in this enſuing Treatiſe; That whilſt we are quarrelling and striving one with another, we can never wreſtle, and strive with God, as we ought to do, in Prayer. And then what mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel is it if iniquity do abound, and the love of many wax cold as it doth? But I ſhall Preface no more, Let it
<pb facs="tcp:121309:9"/> ſuffice, to ſay of this Treatiſe, that it is ſhort and ſweet. Hath in it plenty with much variety, and all couched into a narrow compaſs, ſo as the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is in no danger of being cloyed, as ſome gueſts are wont to be at a great Feaſt, where the ſight of ſo much as is ſerved in, takes off their ſtomacks that they can eat little. Here is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and no more of what is ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly uſeful for all that have but a minde, and good will to pray. And in teſtimony hereof, I ſubſcribe my ſelf an hearty well-willer to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of this Treatiſe, and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders due improvement of it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Ford.</signed>
               <dateline>Exceter
<date>Decem. <hi>16. 1658.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:121309:9"/>
            <head>Mr. SAUNDER'S <hi>PREFACE.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the reſpect I had to the Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, and the content I took in the peruſal of this Tract (being therewith entruſted by him before it was committed to the Preſſe) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then expectation to adde repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to it by prefixing my name, that drew this Epiſtle from me. But if the matter treated of meet with the better entertainment from any, by this means I ſhall count a little time and pains well ſpent. As for the ſubject, 'tis ſuch as needs not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Letters of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or any Panegyrick to
<pb facs="tcp:121309:10"/> uſher it in to an honeſt heart. Yet in our giddy-headed times, 'tis its lot, with all other the ſacred inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Chriſt, to have its legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timateneſſe made matter of diſpute, yea, zealouſly impugned. We read of Hereticks, very ancient, called <hi>Euchitae,</hi> that held men muſt be ever praying,<note place="margin">Aug. de Haer l <hi>1.</hi> De quibus etiam. <hi>Epiphan.</hi>
               </note> but who ever heard before men ſhould never pray? Yes, (for there is no new thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun)<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Clem. Alex. ſtrom. lib. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> mentions an old Hereſie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That men ſhould not pray at all. God gives bleſſings unaskt, Prayer therefore is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuperfluous. Our unhappy times have given a reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to this mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous conceit. I take thee, Reader, to be a Chriſtian; and if thou be ſo indeed, thou knoweſt, thou canſt no more be without Prayer, then thou canſt
<pb facs="tcp:121309:10"/> be without thy food. 'Tis not ſo much thy duty as thy priviledge. Wouldeſt thou pleaſe God? I know thou wouldſt. <hi>The Prayer of the righteous is his delight,</hi> Prov. 15.8. 'Tis like <hi>honey drops,</hi> Cant. 4.11. Sweet to his taſte. <hi>Incenſe</hi> to his noſtrils, <hi>Pſal</hi> 141.2.<note place="margin">Dioniſ. Carth. in Matth.</note> 
               <hi>Carthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> obſerves, that, of all other Chriſtian ſervices, Prayer only is compared to incenſe. In it we ſtrive with God; but he likes ſuch ſtriving. <hi>Haec vis Deo grata eſt,</hi> ſays Tert. <hi>This force is grateful to God.</hi> Wouldeſt thou glorifie God, and pay him the homage thou oweſt him? This is <hi>Cenſus ſubjectionis nostrae,</hi> our ſuit fine, or homage in which God has the glory of all his Attributes returned him:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Solater</hi> on Pſa. 116. <hi>pag.</hi> 194.</note> his All-ſufficiency, Omnipotency, Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Love, Mercy, Dominion, Truth. Is Heaven ſhut againſt thee? This is <hi>Clavis Coeli,</hi> as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin,</hi> The key of Heaven: Not of the <hi>aerial</hi> only; it opens that,
<pb facs="tcp:121309:11"/> as <hi>Elias</hi> prayed for rain and it came: yea, and an <hi>Heathen</hi> Emperour, <hi>M. Aurelius</hi> relates how that in the German Expedition,<note place="margin">Tert. ed ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p. c. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; in apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>log cap. <hi>5.</hi> Juſtia. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pol. <hi>2.</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. l. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> the Chriſtian ſouldiers by their prayers made the clouds to yield down water to his Hoſt, ready to die for thirſt. But 'tis <hi>Clavis Paradiſi,</hi> the key of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe too; by this key maiſt thou get into Gods preſence, and have what thou wilt of him. 'Tis <hi>Res omnipotentiſsima, Luthers</hi> devout <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> a kinde of omnipotent thing, which makes God himſelf to ſay, <hi>Sine me, Let me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,</hi> Exodus 32.10. It does (with reverence be it ſpoken) ſtrangely charm the Majeſty of Heaven. The word which is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cantatio, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>canta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m mum D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i nullis c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> ſe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bus ſuperar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poteſt. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>icani p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>bus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>on. Epist.</note> Iſa. 26.16. ſignifies a <hi>charm.</hi> Feareſt thou the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils aſſaults? 'Tis <hi>Flagellum Satanae</hi> (as <hi>Auſtin</hi>) a whip for Satan, and a bulwark for thee, that is, (ſays
<pb facs="tcp:121309:11"/> 
               <hi>Chryſ.</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Not to be broken, not to be ſhaken. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the ſame Father, a ſtrong weapon. 'Tis both off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſive and defenſive. Deſireſt thou ſweeteſt communion with thy bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our here on earth? This is <hi>Oſculum pacis,</hi> as an Antient ſtyles it, <hi>The kiſſe of peace,</hi> with which the ſoul kiſſeth the lips of her beloved. 'Tis <hi>Sabbathum animae,</hi> as another calls it, the ſouls ſabbath. Wouldſt thou viſit <hi>Canaan</hi> before hand, and get to Heaven once before thou come to ſettle there? Prayer is <hi>ſcala Coeli,</hi> a Ladder for thee. 'Tis <hi>Aſcenſus intellectus ad Deum.</hi> The aſcent of the minde to God, <hi>Damaſcen</hi>'s definition. To be ſhort, 'tis a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicon,</hi> good for every thing, and nothing good without it. <hi>All things are ſanctified by it,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.4, 5.<note place="margin">Weems Chriſt. Synag. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. <hi>3.</hi> Parag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>5</hi>
               </note> All things upheld by it. The <hi>Jews</hi> have a ſaying, <hi>ſine ſtationibus non ſubſiſteret mundus.</hi> The world
<pb facs="tcp:121309:12"/> would not endure without <hi>Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Gnammuda, ſtanding,</hi> is one of the ſeven names they give to Prayer; without this, the world would not ſtand. This rich trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Reader, is here put into thine hand, with direction how to uſe it. Here is not <hi>Novum,</hi> any thing new, but perhaps <hi>Novè,</hi> good old truths in a new and delightful dreſſe. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Authour hath, in this little piece, well mixed <hi>utile dulci,</hi> thou canſt not m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe deſired content in reading it; nor can I chooſe but heartily commend it to thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious peruſal. Read, and practice: but remember, write over thy clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet door what the <hi>Jews</hi> uſe to write about the doors of their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi>
               <note place="margin">They ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it by this Abbr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is the firſt letter of each word. <hi>Bux. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. de Abbr. Heb.</hi>
               </note> A Prayer without af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is like a body without a
<pb facs="tcp:121309:12"/> ſoul. Maintain inward warmth of devotion in thine heart; he that does not, <hi>Loquitur, non precatur</hi> (as ſays <hi>Salvian</hi>) he talks, he does not pray: if thou do,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.28.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Iſrael, becauſe, as a Prince, thou ſhalt have power with God, and with men, and thou ſhalt prevail.</hi> That thou mayeſt is the hearty deſire of him, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Deſirous of the prosperity of thy precious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſoul</hi> RICH. SAUNDERS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:121309:13"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Introduction and opening of the Text. <hi>pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Two Doctrines from it, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, That when we have to do with God in prayer, it is our duty to make uſe of fervency. Secondly, that righteous mens prayers are powerful and effectual. <hi>5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The firſt point opened and proved. <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Prayer deſcribed to be a fervent expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of holy deſires to God only, by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ. <hi>7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>This deſcription of Prayer explained in the ſeveral branches of it, <hi>viz. 1.</hi> It is a fervent expreſſion] Wherein is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, Firſt, What this fervency is? Anſwered in three particulars. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, When are men ſaid to be fervent in prayer? <hi>p. 10.</hi> Anſwered in ſeven things.
<pb facs="tcp:121309:13"/> Thirdly, Why men muſt be thus zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous? <hi>p. 19.</hi> Made good by eight rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons following. <hi>1.</hi> Not becauſe God like man ſtands in need of it. <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe the Lord loves an importunate ſutor. <hi>3.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he that asketh any thing coldly, asketh a denial. <hi>4.</hi> The matter about which you are emploied, is weighty. <hi>5.</hi> There are many and prodigious ſins crying. <hi>6.</hi> By this means we declare at what rate we value Gods mercies. <hi>7.</hi> Fervent-prayer is moſt effectual. <hi>8.</hi> There are other reaſons why the Lord will have it ſo. Firſt, So much the more to aſtoniſh the Devil. Secondly, To give good example to the Church. Thirdly, To bring the hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter temper. <hi>p. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Doctrine farther cleared by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-Preſidents. <hi>p. 27.</hi> Fourthly, How may a man keep his heart i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this height of heavenly fervor and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſtantly, for ſometimes it is ſo? Anſwered. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Uſe 1.</hi> To condemn the Roman ſociety: and too many formal Protestants. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A formal Chriſtian deſcribed in five par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. <hi>1.</hi> He is deſtitute of ſpiritual life and heat. <hi>2.</hi> He ſaith or repeats prayers often, but without zeal. <hi>3.</hi> He
<pb facs="tcp:121309:14"/> is taken up with ſelf-ſeeking and variety of diſtracting cares. <hi>4.</hi> He is oppreſſed with corruption, and carried away with a violent ſtream of wordly cares. <hi>5.</hi> He is not in charity with his neighbour.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Uſe 2.</hi> To excite men to the duty of fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayer. <hi>p. 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Directions for that purpoſe, in three things. To which are annexed three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious motives. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>One weighty Objection anſwered, <hi>viz.</hi> Theſe fervent expreſſions are not always ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſeful, a time may come when a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and a <hi>Samuel</hi> may not be heard. <hi>42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſecond branch of the deſcription of Prayer, <hi>viz.</hi> Of holy deſires] how to be underſtood. They muſt be holy for Perſon, Principle, Matter and End. <hi>43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>First, The Perſon muſt be holy: Farther explained by enquiring firſt, What an holy heart is? Secondly, Why prayer muſt come from an holy heart? <hi>46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, The Principle muſt be holy. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which head is diſcovered, Firſt, Why Prayer muſt come from a ſpiritual prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple? Secondly, How Prayer coming from the Spirit may be diſcerned? <hi>49, 51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, Deſires muſt be holy for the
<pb facs="tcp:121309:14"/> Matter of them, and that <hi>1.</hi> In the ground. <hi>2.</hi> In the matter, inſtanced in ſeveral particulars. <hi>p. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fourthly, Deſires must be holy for the end. Where is diſcovered, <hi>1.</hi> When a mans end is holy? <hi>2.</hi> Why it muſt be ſo? To which reaſons are given, both Philoſophical and Theological. <hi>56, 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Uſe 1.</hi> For correction of thoſe that pray, but in a cold manner. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Marks of ſuch indiſpoſedneſſe to prayer. <hi>60, 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Uſe 2.</hi> For instruction in two things <hi>1.</hi> All prayer will not ſerve the turn. <hi>2.</hi> Learn the art of praying. <hi>62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The third branch of the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcription of Prayer—<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto God] <hi>65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Prayer muſt be directed to God only. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of it. <hi>66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—Only by Jeſus Chriſt.] <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Where is enquired, Firſt, What it is to offer up prayers by Christ? Secondly, Why it muſt be ſo?</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Uſe 1.</hi> Shews the miſery of graceleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in that they cannot pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y. See it diſcovered in two things.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Uſe 2.</hi> To ſhew the duty of all to amend their praying. <hi>74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> are annexed Objections to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:121309:15"/>
               <item>Firſt, What need this ado? leſſe pains may ſerve the turn; God knows our wants, and he will do what ſeemeth good in his ſight. <hi>75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, Some ſay they cannot pray, or at leaſt not according to this deſcription of Prayer. <hi>76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, Many that have uſed thus to pray, have proved counterfeits? Ergo, &amp;c. <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fourthly, Many we ſee have bleſſings of all ſorts, who yet never did, nor could pray thus for them? <hi>82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fifthly, Should we practiſe this duty eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, as is preſſed, it would waſte and ſpend our ſpirits, hinder us in our callings, and expoſe us to the deriſion of others? <hi>84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Caſes of Conſcience to be reſolved, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, What ſhould a man do that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not utter his minde? he wants fit words for ſuch a preſence. <hi>89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, What ſhould he do that findes his heart unfit and altogether indispoſed for prayer, especially with ſuch holy fervency. <hi>92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, I am diſtracted with vain thoughts, and terrified with ſtrange fears, especially when alone and in
<pb facs="tcp:121309:15"/> the dark: what ſhall I do? <hi>98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fourthly, I finde not any ſucceſſe in my prayer, but am rather croſſed in them, therefore I fear it is in vain to pray. <hi>96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fifthly, What ſhould a man ſettle his minde upon while he is framing and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting his prayer? <hi>100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sixthly, But when I do, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thinks my own unworthineſſe doth ſo much the more preſent it ſelf, and make me rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy through fear to ſink. <hi>101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conditions required that pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er may be accepted. <hi>103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>First, The Perſon muſt be ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>htly quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; and that ſtanding in a threefold relation, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> To God. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> To Men. <hi>104</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> To it ſelf. <hi>104, 105</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Five properties of perſons thus qualified. <hi>105</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> It ſeems by this that wicked, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous perſons may no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pray; or if ſo, their prayers will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to little or no purpoſe, ineffectual. <hi>108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, All the graces mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t be ſet on work, <hi>viz.</hi> Faith; where is enquired, how may a man know when he prayeth in faith? <hi>110</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:121309:16"/>
               <item>Repentance, which gives occaſion to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, How true penitency in gracious ſouls may be diſcerned from feigned ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in graceleſſe perſons? <hi>114, 115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Humility. <hi>Q.</hi> How this grace may be diſcerned? <hi>117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Motives to fervent prayer drawn
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> From the Lord. <hi>120, 121</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> From Men. <hi>125</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> From prayer it ſelf. <hi>130</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Anſwered with respect to ſuch perſons as were effectual in prayer. <hi>132</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Second Doctrine, <hi>134</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proved by Scripture. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Explained by enquiring,
<list>
                     <item>Firſt, Wherein they are ſo prevailing? <hi>135</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Secondly, Why they are ſo prevalent? <hi>139</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Uſe 1.</hi> To let us ſee what to expect from the prayers of too many among us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, unholy. <hi>142</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Uſe 2.</hi> To ſhew us what to do that we may be powerful and effectual in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Firſt, get the qualification in the Text. <hi>143</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Secondly, Pray in a time while he may be
<pb facs="tcp:121309:16"/> found. <hi>p. 144</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>When theſe two are joined, prayer never failed.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> When they are joined in Perſons.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> When they are joined in a Nation. <hi>145</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> When will that be? <hi>146</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> It hath been often promiſed.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> This is the way whereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll thoſe that belong to God may be brought in. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Cauſes diſcovered, why prayers have been ſo ineffectual. <hi>147</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Directions how to prevail more. <hi>151</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:121309:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121309:17"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF PRAYER.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JAMES 5.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—The effectual ferven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Prayer of a righteous man, availeth much.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Spring-head of this <hi>Scripture</hi> doth ariſe at the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>verſe</hi> of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the ſtreams run down to the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. The general ſcope of the whole, is to give direction in a matter of no ſmall concernment, <hi>viz.</hi> how the <hi>Flock</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:121309:18"/> of Chriſt ſhould demean themſelves in every condition <hi>Divine</hi> providence might cut out for them in the <hi>preſent evil world.</hi> According to our <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> whoſe pen was held and ruled by the <hi>Spirit of truth,</hi> the ſtate of the Church, and as here deſcribed, is two-fold, <hi>Proſperity</hi> and <hi>Adverſity,</hi> happineſſe and miſery, frowns and ſmiles; like the <hi>Sun</hi> which ſometimes appears bright and glorious, but ſometimes is hid under dusky clouds; now in <hi>health,</hi> then in an <hi>Hectick: weeping</hi> and <hi>joy;</hi> a <hi>ſummers</hi> day and a <hi>winters</hi> night, as ſhe gives her own <hi>motto,</hi> Pſal. 102.10. <hi>Thou haſt life me up and caſt me down:</hi> an uncertain c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and ſuch as wants peculiar di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, eſpecially if it be conſidered how eaſie it is to miſcarry in both.</p>
            <p>He that runs may read the purpoſe of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> to ballaſt the <hi>people of God</hi> in this unequal condition, to help them walk ſteadily both in their up-hill and down-hill way; <hi>Is any afflicted?</hi> then, <hi>let him pray: Is any merry?</hi> then, <hi>let him ſing Pſalms.</hi> Needfull it is for <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to be doing in each con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>My Text is a branch of the firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121309:18"/> and is laid down as a Motive and Encouragement to the duty, drawn from the excellent ſucceſſe of it, which he proves by induction of particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in the following verſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The words in themſelves are a good mans encouragement and teſtimoniall, ſubſcribed by God himſelf, which doth certifie, what he is, and what he muſt be, <hi>viz.</hi> Fervent in prayer.</p>
            <p>They are eaſie in the ſenſe of them, clear and plain; it will be time and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſpent impertinently, to give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count what <hi>Interpreters</hi> ſay of them, how they differ or agree; this were almoſt to ſtrike fire and light up a candle at noon-day, to ſeek for that which is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hid nor loſt. As for part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent confuſion, and to clear our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, I ſhall divide the handling of them into three generals; In them we have to conſider,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or duty commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and directed unto, <hi>viz. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayer.</hi> A neceſſary and uſefull duty, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>decree</hi> of God in regard of its immutability, nor the <hi>promiſe</hi> of God in regard of its infallibility,<note place="margin">Ezek. 36. v. 37.</note> nor the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual interceſſion of <hi>Chriſt our Lord,</hi> who
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121309:19"/> taught his Diſciples to pray, can diſpenſe with us for not doing it. The Goſpel commands it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or quallifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion mentioned, which is two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, Of the duty; it muſt be <hi>fervent,</hi> ſuch as ſets the whole man on work, and ſuch as notes the moſt lively activity that can be. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>is ardens,</hi> 1. <hi>fervent,</hi> as <hi>Piſcator</hi> renders it; <hi>Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cax, i.</hi> effectual, as <hi>Beza.</hi> It is both, <hi>effectual-fervent,</hi> as in the text. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Of the perſon, he muſt <hi>be righteous, i.</hi> ſo made by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt by faith: juſtified by righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe impured, called <hi>the righteouſneſſe of God;</hi> ſanctified by righteouſneſſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, called <hi>ours,</hi> becauſe inherent in us. They muſt be men of penitent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed hearts, men of faith, <hi>evangelically</hi> righteous.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or effect, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and good iſſue of prayer ſo quallifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and performed, <hi>It availeth much;</hi> they are prayers that carry force with them; thus quallified, they are a mighty <hi>engine</hi> to move heaven and earth, a <hi>key</hi> to open the door of the treaſury of God, to fetch mercies for our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121309:19"/> a <hi>Panecaea,</hi> a receipt for every di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, and a ſoveraign one too, it brings preſent eaſe and future health. God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaid to the ſeed of <hi>Jacob, Seek ye my face in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parts thus ſet, we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſily read the meaning of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in them. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the firſt, I ſhall handle the two later, and labour to condeſcend to the meaneſt capacity, and point out the full ſcope of the words in two uſefull Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That when we have to do with God in prayer, it is our duty to make uſe of ſtrength and fervency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That righteous m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns prayers are powerfull and effectual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both theſe obſervations (God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) I ſhall labour to explain, laying them as the foundation of my intended Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, <hi>viz. That when we have to do with God in prayer, it is our duty to uſe ſtrength and fervency.</hi> I ſhall prove this Doctrine, firſt, by Scripture preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents and precepts. We muſt put to our ſtrength, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for <hi>Sodom,</hi> Gen. 18. and as <hi>Jacob</hi> in wreſtling with the Angel,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121309:20"/> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. <hi>v.</hi> 26. who held with his hand, when his thigh was lamed. <hi>Moſes</hi> in praying for the people, craving leave for himſelf to enter <hi>Canaan,</hi> how earneſt was he with God? how doth he work it out? The woman in the Goſpel was full of this heat, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.25. She will not be ſaid <hi>nay,</hi> like another <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> ſhe threatens heaven, and is modeſtly impudent; and I think it was for that end Chriſt held her off ſo long. We may ſee it enjoyned in general, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy ſtrength;</hi> what we do to or for God, it muſt be done <hi>cum toto valdè,</hi> with all our might. Preſſed and practiſed in particulars, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Cry out and ſhout thou inhabitant of Zion! Exod.</hi> 14.15. <hi>Moſes</hi> cried to the Lord. The Ninevites cry mightily to God, <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.8. It notes the ſtrength of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. <hi>Elijah</hi> cried earneſtly to God, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.17. Chriſt as Mediator ſent up <hi>ſtrong cries</hi> to his Father, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7. He prayed as he preached: He preached, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>one having authority,</hi> and he prayed likewiſe powerfully and effectually. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth the Saints,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121309:20"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to ſtrive together in prayer to God,</hi> Rom. 15.30. A military word he uſeth, noting ſuch fervency as is for life and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th; as he teſtifieth of himſelf, that he prayed night and day. The Primi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans at their ſervices and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>votions, with one ſhoulder were ſo earneſt, that they ſeemed to beſiege the Throne of grace, to raiſe a common force and ſtrength to invade and uſe violence with God in prayer; as it is related by <hi>Tertullian, Apol.</hi> 39.</p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this point, I intend this method, <hi>viz.</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ew what <hi>prayer,</hi> and what fervent prayer i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and applying the deſcription fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer is a fervent expreſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of holy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to God, only by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is to pray fervently, <hi>Orationi inſtare, &amp; fortiter incumbere</hi> Col. 4.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Continue in prayer,</hi> which implies both intention of minde, and aſſiduity in the exerciſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay, <hi>it is a fervent expreſſion</hi>] So much theſe ordinary tearms uſed in Scripture do import, as, <hi>calling out of the deep,</hi> pouring out of the ſoul, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121309:21"/> 
               <hi>crying</hi> to heaven; expreſſed alſo in other Scriptures: 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.20. <hi>Hezekiah the King, and Iſaiah the Prophet prayed and cried to heaven, Luke</hi> 18-1. Men ought alwaies to pray, and <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>the elect cry day and night.</hi> I ſhall labour as fully as I can, to unfold what I have read and obſerved touching this fervour in prayer; and enquire.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> Firſt, What this <hi>fervencie</hi> is?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We may conceive the nature of it in theſe three following branches, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is the very <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at</hi> and <hi>height</hi> of all gracious affections, in a Zealous moving o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſoul <hi>to God</hi> in prayer, and <hi>for God</hi> after prayer; where there is no Zeal <hi>for</hi> him, there is little to him: and again, where there is none to him in our prayers, commonly there is none for him in our actions; he that is <hi>cold</hi> in prayer, is not <hi>hot</hi> in any <hi>good</hi> cauſe, except where <hi>ſelf</hi> is principle or end. Though I do confeſſe diverſity of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in <hi>Zeal</hi> to God, and for God, which are diverſly manifeſted, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times eclipſed in Gods deareſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, beſt skill'd, and moſt exerciſed in prayer.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:121309:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Fervency,</hi> is the influence, and <hi>efficacy</hi> of the regenerating <hi>Spirit</hi> of Chriſt, helping his own needy members to pray, ſo as they may be he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>The ſpirit helpeth our infirmities,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. <hi>I will pray w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> —Though you be we k, yet <hi>the Spirit</hi> is <hi>willing</hi> and <hi>ſtrong;</hi> And ſo much onely as cometh in our prayers from the <hi>renewed</hi> part, findes accept<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce with God; If the motion be good, he will not accept it from an ill mouth, nor own theſe prayers, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited by the <hi>Spirit of grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is a reverently-Zealous manifeſtation of both; the former, in words ſutable, for matter and manner, to a renewed mind, as may be moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to the hearers, if it be publick; the heart is the fountain of this heat and life, the tongue is but an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and God looks chiefly to the firſt; <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Hannah</hi> prayed fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently to God, and yet ſpake little or nothing: The latter is for mans ſake.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We enquire, when are <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> men ſaid to be <hi>fervent</hi> in <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121309:22"/> in dealing with God to uſe their <hi>ſtrength?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer in the enſuing particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> When they are moved by the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of adoption, Rom.</hi> 8.15. and 26. compared: <hi>Ye have received the Spirit of adoption, whereby we cry Abba, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and, the Spirit helpeth our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> Then a man prayeth with ſtrength, when the <hi>Spirit helpeth.</hi> The ſame word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e. Spirit,</hi> is attributed both to the <hi>Spirit</hi> of man, and to the holy Ghoſt, or <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> becauſe as that gives motion and operation to the body, which of it ſelf could never performe; ſo doth the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> to thoſe that partake of it. Hence of <hi>Stephen</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when they performed any nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exploit of grace, it is ſaid, <hi>they were filled with the holy Ghoſt.</hi> The heart of man indeed is but as ſo much cold earth, till the Spirit of adoption inflame it, and when this is gone, all the ſtrength is gone; as a wheel that is turned about with an hand, if the hand be removed, the wheel ſtandeth ſtill. The duty is we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k and empty till the <hi>Spirit</hi> overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow the ſoul, and then it is a living bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. We know, of old, the Symboles of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121309:22"/> the <hi>Spirit</hi> were <hi>fiery tongues,</hi> and where this fire is, it melts the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ice, its heavenly flame appears in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uty. As <hi>Eliahs</hi> body was carried up with a whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind, and a fiery Chariot to heaven, ſo are gracious ſouls moved by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God in prayer: for as its motions are <hi>regular,</hi> in regard of the <hi>object,</hi> ſo they are <hi>vehement</hi> in regard of the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> When men are inwardly heated with a <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>feeling</hi> of what they pray for. <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark roſe higher, as the waters grew higher; want will adde ſticks to the fire and make the flame more fervent. Hence co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>groans unutterable,</hi> earneſt ejaculations, like darts ſhot up to heaven. <hi>David</hi> is an exact pattern for this, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1, 2, 3. <hi>As the Hart panteth after the water-brooks, ſo panteth my ſoul after thee O God! my ſoul thirſteth for God, for the living God, &amp;c.</hi> As a child, as ſoon as it comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, begins with cries and tears, becauſe of its indigency: ſo where there is any ſpiritual <hi>life</hi> and <hi>heat,</hi> the firſt diſcoveries of it, are by <hi>ſighs and groans.</hi> Beggars cry earneſtly from ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of want, as the blind man
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121309:23"/> did, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.41. <hi>O thou ſon of David have mercy on me!</hi> And as the Apoſtles did, <hi>Lord ſave or we periſh!</hi> When a man praies as <hi>Rachel</hi> whilſt ſhe ſpake to <hi>Jacob, Give me children or I die!</hi> or as <hi>Hannah,</hi> 1 Sam. 1.13. who ſpake <hi>in her heart,</hi> then he is fervent. For as many beams of the ſun meeting in a glaſſe do beget a burning, ſo are the ſpirits and faculties conjoyned and heated in prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> When tongue and tears are the index of a melting heart, then men may be ſaid to be fervent in prayer. Thus <hi>David</hi> diſcovers his work in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.2. <hi>Attend to me and hear me; I mourn in my complaints and make a noiſe:</hi> he bent, as it were, all his nerves, and ſet up his note. So doth <hi>Hannah,</hi> 1 Sam. 1.10. when ſhe is ſaid to be <hi>in bitterneſſe of ſpirit, and prayed to the Lord and wept ſore. Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> manifeſted her fervency, by thoſe ſtreams of tears that ran through her ſupplications. I do not ſay, that the ſtrength and work of prayer doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in extenſion of the voice, or vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of pronunciation: <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Hannah</hi> prayed fervently, and yet ſpake
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121309:23"/> not a word;] neither do I judge tears unſeparable from effectual Prayer; But, this I ſay, that the voice may be much helpful to increaſe devotion and to move compaſſion, and when tears do accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, they are good ſymptomes, as <hi>Calvin</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Lachrymae non ſunt vera poenitentia, at affectus &amp; ſymbola poenitentiae.</hi> They have ſtrength and a voice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s well as words, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.8. <hi>The Lord hath heard the voice of my weeping! (lachrymae, ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra vocis habent.)</hi> As muſick on the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſounds farther and more harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly then on dry land, ſo do prayers joyned with tears, cry louder in the ears of God, and make ſweeter melody, then when they be abſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> When a man borroweth ſtrength, and getteth hands to joyn with him. Wo to him that is alone; Society is uſefull both in preaching and in praying. Therefore our Saviour ſent out his diſciples by two and two; <hi>(vis unita fortior:)</hi> as the gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of waters make the ſtream ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the voices of many together, the louder ſound; So it is here, ſingle prayer is like the ſingle hair of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> but thoſe of a Congregation like the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121309:24"/> whole buſh. <hi>Deus pluris facit preces in Eccleſiâ quàm domi factas, non ob locum, ſed ob conſiderationem multitudinis fidelium, Deus communi conſenſu invocantium,</hi> as <hi>Rivet</hi> notes. As thoſe uſe to do who would fain ſpeed in their Petitions to great men, they get hands, others to joyn in pleading and ſpeaking for them, ſo it is here; yet underſtand this <hi>inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively,</hi> you muſt pray your ſelves and for your ſelves: Not as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who put it wholly on others, <hi>Orate pro nobis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> When men are frequent and conſtant in Prayer, ſo as to receive no deniall, diſcouragements and worldly impediments notwithſtanding. Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity carrieth fervency in its bowels. <hi>Jacob</hi> would not let the <hi>Angel</hi> go till he bleſſed him, and will ſtand to it though upon one leg. <hi>Hannah</hi> multiplied to pray, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Paul</hi> ſought the Lord thrice, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8. <hi>i. e.</hi> frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fervently: He is adviſing men to <hi>pray continually; i. e.</hi> habitually, <hi>vitally. Coloſ.</hi> 4.2.<note place="margin">Semper orat, qui bene ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per agit.</note> 
               <hi>Wait upon prayer,</hi> perſevere with ſtrength; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: The word is attributed to the hunting of Dogs, which will not ceaſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121309:24"/> the game till they have got it: And <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.12. <hi>continuing, watching in prayer,</hi> it imports conſtancy with vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency. And this was the practice of that poor woman, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.22. <hi>Have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on me thou ſon of Daevid,</hi> &amp;c. And after denials ſhe riſes higher, and locks her ſelf within the deniall, and pleads Gods truth and juſtice, if mercy will nor ſerve, let thy words be true, <hi>I am a Dog,</hi> and there is ſomething for <hi>Dogs,</hi> let me have a <hi>Dogs</hi> portion, <hi>crumbs,</hi> I crave no mo e. <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> prayed thrice a day, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhiles ſeven times: Of ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous <hi>Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> it is reported that he conſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſix times a day, <hi>viz.</hi> twice by himſelf alone, twice with his wife, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd twice with his family. And of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> that pious <hi>Emperour, (Cujus regia non diſſimilis crat monaſterio)</hi> that his Court was like a Church for piety and devotion; Of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, that he converſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more with God then with men. All men of might in Prayer. Conſtancy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakes fervency.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> When in Prayers men do heat others by the beauty and livelineſſe of a well-order'd working prayer. A living coal will inliven others, and one candle
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121309:25"/> lighteth others. Grace where it is, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to kindle where it is not: as where is life, there is alſo a ſeminary of propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and the more excellent the life is, the more pregnant is it to propagate in its kinde: like the glow-iron on the Smiths Anvill, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſting light and heat round about it. But becauſe this may be brought about by one who is not formally fervent, <hi>effectively</hi> (as the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher ſpeaks of the ſun) there are ſome cautions to be added to this mark: In ſuch a zealous petitioner, who heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth others with the fervency of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, there is required, Firſt, a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of that miſery which the voice decipher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, both in confeſſion of ſin and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation of judgements. Secondly, A grounded <hi>hope</hi> of relief upon experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſome promiſes. Thirdly, <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity</hi> in the Petitioner: the truth ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken muſt be in the inward parts, that what is asked of God, be for God, for his ſervice and glory; as <hi>Hannah</hi> in her <hi>Samuel.</hi> There may be an inward cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and yet an outward heat, (the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Amber-ſtone</hi>) as in hypocrites who know much of God, bur do little for him; this may heat and benefit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121309:25"/> though not themſelves. Again, there may be an inward hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and for ſome time in ſome duties, yet no audible expreſſions, as in <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Hannah,</hi> they <hi>cryed to the Lord and yet ſaid nothing:</hi> their heat was as a flame kept in, encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. This zeal in prayer is moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, as the <hi>prime</hi> object of his eye, and ear, although no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall to men; for unleſſe the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner burn with zealous heat and expreſſe it, he ſhall never enflame the heart of the hearers nor quicken their devotion: as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Enar. in Pſal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> When men joyn endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and other things ſeaſonable and uſefull together with Prayer. As the wiſe mariner who hath not onely an <hi>eye</hi> to the <hi>Star,</hi> but an <hi>hand</hi> to the <hi>Helm:</hi> and as the Plowmen of <hi>Sparta,</hi> who had one hand held up to <hi>Ceres,</hi> whom they feigned the <hi>Goddeſs</hi> of corn, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the ſtilts of the plow: they joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed plowing and praying. The good man not onely lifts up his <hi>heart</hi> to heaven, but puts his hand to the work, to compaſſe what he prayes for. The <hi>Heathen</hi> could ſay, <hi>admota manu, invocanda eſt Minerva:</hi> and they noted him for a fooliſh Carter,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121309:26"/> that when his Cart ſtuck faſt, cried to God, and moved his lips, but not his hands to help himſelf. <hi>Semper orare, eſt ſemper operari,</hi> Aug. <hi>If thou calleſt for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) and crieſt for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding:</hi> there is Prayer to God; <hi>If thou ſeek her as ſilver, and ſearcheſt for her as for hid treaſure,</hi> there is mans endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in the uſe of means. Many things are requiſite to prayer, according to the nature of the bleſſing: if <hi>Spiritual,</hi> then <hi>faſting</hi> and <hi>almes,</hi> as <hi>Cornelius</hi> practiſed, <hi>Acts.</hi> 10. <hi>Repentance</hi> and Prayer, as the <hi>Ninevites</hi> did, <hi>Jon.</hi> 3.8. Hearing the Word and uſe of the Sacraments, which are inſtituted meanes for accompliſhing great and ſaving ends. And ſo, if the bleſſing be temporall; Vain are deſires not produced to action. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> writeth of the <hi>Bathes</hi> in the <hi>Parthecuſian</hi> Iſlands, that they are fiery hot, but ſend forth no flames; that fervency cannot be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, which is ſmother'd and pent up in the heart, gets no vent, hath no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecall operation. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> relates it as a vanity of his youth, that he prayed God againſt ſome ſins whereunto he was ſtrongly addicted, but ſhould have been full ſorrowfull if God ſhould have heard
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121309:26"/> him, becauſe he was loth to part with them; how much better was that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Domine Deus fac me in conſequendis iis operam collocare, pro quibus obtinendis, ſoleo ad Te orare; i.</hi> O Lord help me to beſtow pains in getting thoſe things, for obtaining of which, I uſually pray unto thee.</p>
            <p>Confeſſe ſin you muſt and not ſleight, pray for pardon and power, with deſire and longing after them; not as <hi>Auſtin</hi> did with a ſecret reſervation; or as <hi>Spira</hi> and the hypocrite, who pray for grace, but ſaw no beauty in it why it ſhould be deſired; ſaved without it they cannot be, that they only appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend: But rather ſay with <hi>David, My heart is prepared, O God, my heart is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared;</hi> and with <hi>Paul, I will pray with the Spirit and with underſtanding.</hi> This is to work in prayer, to uſe ſtrength and fervency. Now is the ſoul on the mount of transfiguration, this is to pray in prayer, and the ſecond Queſtion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Why muſt men be thus <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> zealous and fervent in prayer?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, <hi>Firſt,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Not becauſe God (like men) ſtandeth in need of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121309:27"/> of Examination for diſcovery: nothing is hid from him: he is omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient: as he heareth without ears, ſo he underſtandeth without words. And yet it muſt be ſo for theſe reaſons, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, That you may acknowledge <hi>his Propriety</hi> (even as children do their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when they come for food) in the good things you want, and receive them with more joy and thankfulneſſe. God will be owned, and have his <hi>Lordly-right</hi> acknowledged; If we take any thing that is our neighbours without asking them leave, we ſhall be accounted theeves, ſo, to take and poſſeſſe the things of God, without asking his leave, will be accounted felony of the higheſt nature. Secondly, That you may learn to diſtinguiſh between gifts of <hi>promiſe,</hi> and of <hi>common</hi> providence: the firſt are effects of <hi>ſpecial</hi> grace, requiring faith and prayer, <hi>(I will be ſought unto by the houſe of Iſrael:)</hi> the latter are fruits of <hi>common</hi> goodneſſe, flowing from that fountain according to his unchangeable purpoſe, for the ſupportance of creatures, till they attain their pre-ordained ends; the firſt are peculiar to the good only; the ſecond common (as the ſun) to good
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121309:27"/> and bad. Thirdly, That by this famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar entercourſe between God and the ſoul, your graces may be both exerciſed and increaſed; that hereby, I ſay, we may have communion with God, and grow into acquaintance with him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſtock of grace is much augmented; as good company doth increaſe it, ſo doth converſe with God much more: ſet this duty aſide, and man becomes a ſtranger to God, his graces decay, and he becomes cold and looſe. This is the firſt reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe the Lord loves an <hi>importunate</hi> ſutor. Fervency, like roſin to the ſtrings of a muſicall inſtrument, makes the ſound pleaſant. <hi>Haec vis gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Deo eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi> It doth, as it were, charm God: it is a weapon well managed that overcomes the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible:</hi> a cord that binds the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as <hi>Jerom</hi> phraſeth it. It is a ſtrength he hath promiſed to yield unto, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.11. <hi>Command ye me;</hi> as ſome gloſſe the place. As they write of <hi>Proteus,</hi> that when any came to conſult with, and to receive Oracles from him, he would firſt turn himſelf into a thouſand ſhapes and varieties of colours, but if they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121309:28"/> preſſed him with importunity, and held him cloſe to it, he then would give them ſatisfactory Oracles. God may indeed ſeem to ſlight the prayer of his people (as we ſlight a confuſed noiſe) and wind himſelf from them, but when they grow fervent, then he lets them to be their own carvers. It will <hi>bow down his ear,</hi> and pull the hand out of his boſom; to ſpeak with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.18. <hi>He is nigh to them that call upon him in truth.</hi> The Canaanitiſh woman is put off three times, and her fervency is crowned with ſucceſſe. It is recorded to the everlaſting renown of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.37. that in every ſervice of God <hi>he acted with all his might, and he proſpered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe he that asketh any thing coldly, doth but teach a deniall. Careleſſe, heartleſſe prayer, is one of the moſt unſavoury parts of formallity, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable, unpleaſing to God; as a body without a ſoul, as incenſe without fire, ſay the <hi>Jews.</hi> Yea and to men unprofitable: as a <hi>Diamond</hi> that is not right, and as a <hi>Picture</hi> not drawn to the life, are of no value. Formall cold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, like <hi>Caeſars</hi> heartleſſe ſacrifice,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121309:28"/> will never finde acceptance. Painted fire as it hath no heat, ſo it is of no uſe. We may as ſoon cleave a rock with a wedge of wood, graſp the winde in our hand, as make carnal cold affections to draw any thing from God. There is no great odds between the omiſſion of duty, and the careleſſe performance of it, man is loſer both ways. The Bow that is ſlack bent, carries not the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to the mark; formality and cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe deſtroy the very vertue of prayer, as doth Garlick the drawing vertue of the <hi>loadſtone,</hi> applyed to it. Therefore we muſt be fervent. We muſt be fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſeekers, before we can be happy enjoyers; God will have us <hi>Jacobs,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhall be <hi>Iſraels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The matter about which you are employed is weighty, and of great concernment; <hi>viz.</hi> to procure pardon and power over ſin, ſupportance under temptations; Giant-like corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſons of <hi>Anack</hi> to prevail over: removal of Judgments, renewed peace after much treachery and hoſtility. Now theſe are not matters of an inferiour <hi>alloy:</hi> they are things not to be obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a ſingle ſigh; oppoſition from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121309:29"/> earth and hell is not to be conquered with a ſleight breath. It is not a dull wiſh, a languiſhing velleity, an heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe endeavour that will win the day. There muſt be paſſionate longings and breakings of heart, with continual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires after God. Great ſtones (you know) are not to be turned over with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great ſtrength: and great mercies are not to be obtained without great ſtrivings. The matters we pray for, require fired affections, enlarged peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; as the Heathen ſaid, <hi>Imperia quolibet pretio conſtant lenè:</hi> a Kingdom cannot be bought too dear; <hi>Agrippina</hi> thought the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire a good pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyworth, paying her life for it, though for her <hi>Nero.</hi> We cannot lay out too much ſtrength, in obtaining objects of ſo great worth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> There are many and prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſins cry aloud to God, in your own breaſts, families, place and Country, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Nation wherein you live; we are like the land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which though it bring forth <hi>multa ſalubria,</hi> yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all it brings forth <hi>plurima venena:</hi> in our Garden are many pleaſant Flowers, but withal more poiſonful, unſavoury
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121309:29"/> weeds; if we look within or without, almoſt all things are to be ſound as the Phyſitians <hi>facies hypocratica</hi> of a dying man, very gaſtly, and <hi>tantum non</hi> deadly; the whole head is ſick; ſin cryes aloud, and, if you be not earneſt indeed, will out-cry your prayers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> By this means we declare at what rate we value Gods ſavour and mercies. A fervent requeſt doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the perſon and thing petitioned for. It is an argument we diſeſteem and undervalue the bleſſing, that we think may be obtained by ſlender peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ns, as if the purchaſe we were about, would not quit the coſt, nor be worth the pains that is required for it. When <hi>Callidius</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Oratour pleaded a cauſe but faintly, and exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſed lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no affection, <hi>Tully</hi> told him, that ſure he was not in earneſt, otherwiſe the tide of affection would have been up; in like manner, it is an argument we reckon not much the bleſſing, when we are faint in our purſuits after it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Fervent prayer is beſt and moſt effectual: like an arrow ſhot with full ſtrength, and a ſhip carryed on with full ſails. Powder and ſhot in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121309:30"/> Muſquet will do no execution, unleſſe the Souldier gives fire well: Prayers without fervency are but as powder and ſhot without fire, they will never go off ſo as to reach Heaven or our wants. Of all elements that of fire is neereſt Heaven, and the more fire in any thing, the higher it aſcends Heaven-ward; cold and ſluggiſh prayers have ſo much earth in them, that like the Graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, if they mount a little upward, they are preſently down again, fall ſhort of Heaven. Of all warlike Engins, your Granadoes and Fire-works are of moſt force; and of all prayers, thoſe that have moſt fervency, are moſt effectual.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Lord will have you to be fervent; Firſt, To the end you may ſo much the more anger and aſtoniſh the Devil, who is eaten up with envy to ſee God ſo much honoured; the inward heat and voice of the heart he cannot hear, <hi>divine</hi> at it he may: but outward expreſſions he doth note and obſerve. Secondly, To give good example to the Church, who are much moved and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up by prayer, eſpecially if it be <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent;</hi> as in the body of an Army, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current ſhoutings of Souldiers do as it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121309:30"/> were infuſe mutually ſpirits into one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Thirdly, To bring the heart into a better temper, which is enlarged and made more capable of ſpiritual bleſſings by this fervency. A zealous petitioner is but preparing and enlarging his rooms to ſtore up the return of his holy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures. Thus you may anſwer the queſtion of the rich man, <hi>What ſhall I do, becauſe I have no room to beſtow my fruit?</hi> A manifeſt ſign they were never gotten by prayer; it makes room before the bleſſing comes; he that is much in fervent prayer, ſhall never be brought into ſuch a ſtreight of vexing cares. And thus you have the third Quere diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and it ſhall now ſuffice, onely a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to clear your judgments, and help you in practice by ſome preſidents.</p>
            <p>I refer you to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 32.11, 12, 13. he doth as it were put God to it, to free himſelf: as if <hi>Moſes</hi> his Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were ſtronger then Gods indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. To <hi>Joſhuah c.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7, 8, 9. he rent his cloaths, fell to the earth on his face before the Ark of the Lord, &amp;c. there is fervency in the very man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and ſo in the matter of his prayer; <hi>Alas, O Lord God, wherefore haſt thou
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121309:31"/> at all brought this great people over Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan, to deliver us into the hands of the</hi> Amorites? <hi>What ſhall I ſay when Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael turneth their back before the enemy? What wilt thou do unto thy great Name?</hi> To <hi>David</hi> in moſt of his <hi>Pſalms.</hi> To <hi>Ezra c.</hi> 9.56. <hi>O Lord God of Heaven, the great and terrible God, &amp;c. Let thine ear now be attentive, and thine eyes open, that thou maiſt hear the prayer of thy ſervant which I pray before thee day and night.</hi> And to <hi>Daniel c.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4. He ſet his face to ſeek the Lord by ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and prayer, with faſting, ſackcloth and aſhes, ſaying, <hi>O Lord, the great and dreadful God, keeping Covenant and Mercy, &amp;c. we have ſinned and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted iniquity, and have done wickedly, &amp;c.</hi> as you may farther read. I come to a fourth Quere, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, How may a man keep his heart in this height of heavenly fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and that conſtantly, for ſometime it is ſo?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, <hi>Firſt,</hi> By <hi>ſoundneſſe</hi> and <hi>depth</hi> of ſpiritual union between Chriſt and the ſoul; (who is the Fountain of ſpiritual life and heat, as the Sun is the Fountain of all life and heat to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121309:31"/> things) as alſo, between you and the members of Chriſt where you live: they pray moſt fervently, that love moſt entirely; therefore S. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter</hi> advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth men and their wives <hi>to live lovingly together, leſt their prayers ſhould be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</hi> How much enmity and ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe do hinder prayers, the common enemy of mankind knoweth well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; he is buſie in ſowing cares, and glad to ſee men divided, for, then they cannot uſe this ſpiritual weapon againſt him, nor weild <hi>this</hi> inſtrument, one of the chiefeſt Engines to batter down the gates of Hell. To make much of thoſe that are godly, is a ready way by allurement to make others good: let this band be ſtrong, and your prayers cannot be weak.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By <hi>dependance</hi> on the ſtrength of God, and not upon your own abilities or graces; this is to fetch fire from Heaven, becauſe no ſacrifice muſt be offered up with common fire. Our ſtrength is weakneſſe, and it is one of Gods names, <hi>the Strength of Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.19. When the wheel is ſet on going, the ſoul ſet on work, how long will it hold to its motion? No
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121309:32"/> longer then turned by the ſame hand that firſt moved it. We ſhall ſoon work out the ſtrength received; and therefore to maintain the vigour of a fervent courſe, there muſt be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrength from Heaven every day. This <hi>David</hi> knew, and therefore when his heart was in good frame as ever he felt it, and his people likewiſe by their free-will-offering declared ſo much in themſelves; yet even then he prays, that God <hi>would keep this for ever in the imagination of the thoughts of the heart of his people, and eſtabliſh their heart in them,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.18. He adored the mercy that made them willing, and then implores his farther grace to ſtrengthen them. Would a Chriſtian pray? Where elſe will he finde mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials for his prayer? Alas! he knows not how, or what to pray for as he ought. God puts words into his mouth, and theſe would freeze there, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vent, did he not by the ſame influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſome heart-heating affections prevail to thaw the tap. In a word, a Chriſtian hath not a ſpark of this fire on his own hearth, except ſome that is ſtrange fire, which will not ſerve the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121309:32"/> turn, he muſt fetch it from Heaven continually.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By a continual ſuppoſal that the preſent opportunity may be the laſt; how earneſt would you pray, how fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent would you be, were you to dye preſently? provided this be in earneſt, ſettled on a grounded knowledge of your mortality, the uncertainty of the laſt hour: elſe this alſo will degenerate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to formality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> By weighing the cauſes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving unto and requiring this fervency; as, fear of Gods diſpleaſure, of the curſe, of the ſentence of death, and of Hell following. Want of Gods image and love of Chriſt, and his grace; immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent judgments hanging over our heads, ready to fall every moment, with ſome hope of ſpeeding in our requeſts, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who hath ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall reap if you faint not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> By a true love unto that we pray for. Strong affections cauſe fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayers. True love makes weak things ſtrong: it is as an addition of fire to the flame. It was love to God that made <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo fervent: <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> ſo earneſt. It hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121309:33"/> vertue: it made the dumb ſon to ſpeak. Love if true, will make a man do that's be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ond his power; as the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> when they were poor in eſtate, yet were rich in liberality. Chriſt loving <hi>Lazarus</hi> well, wept and groaned in ſpirit, when he prayed for him: and ſo did <hi>David</hi> for his ſon. Where affection is wanting, there will be cold praying; we ſee it in ſutors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> By a propoſal of ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving preſidents; as of a poor man that comes to your door for an alms; hear how he cries, with hands and eyes lift up, he multiplieth and continueth Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, <hi>For the Lords ſake, for Chriſts ſake ſome relief!</hi> Of one naked and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſtarved, ſee and behold he will have no denial. Or of a condemned priſoner at the bar, <hi>his knees are bowed to the ground, as if his heart would touch the Judges feet, his hands elevated, his looks ruful, his eyes full of diſtilling tears, his words earneſt and conſtant, Mercy, O Merciful Judge, ſave or I periſh!</hi> Set theſe patterns before you, and make their caſe your own. Be earneſt, the matter is weighty, you muſt either
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121309:33"/> ſpeed there, or no where, now or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>I ſhall apply this in a few things. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Uſe may ſerve to condemn, as the ſociety of <hi>Rome,</hi> requiring and reſting in the work done; whether mighty or weak, hot or cold, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire not, ſo the number and tale be up: So, too many among our ſelves, that content themſelves with a cold and careleſſe form of praying, a bedulling ſtrain, like the pace the <hi>Spaniard</hi> is ſaid to ride. Let us take a character of them: <hi>Firſt,</hi> Such as are deſtitute of ſpiritual life and heat, who have no grounded hope in any promiſe of ſpeeding. How ſhould they pray lively that want life? When life goeth out of the body it groweth cold, and ſo where the life of grace is not, all is cold, no vigour, no zeal, in the diſcharge of duty. <hi>The dead do not praiſe thee,</hi> neither can they pray unto thee, O Lord! <hi>Secondly,</hi> They are meerly formal in Prayer, who ſay or repeat Prayers often, but without any zeal, or ſerious bent of minde to the paſſages thereof, as if they cared not whether they were heard or no. <hi>Negare docent, qui frigide rogant.</hi> Such perſons
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121309:34"/> do far rather ſuggeſt a denial then move pitty; it was hinted before. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> All they who are wholly taken up with ſelf-ſeeking and variety of diſtracting employments, ſo that they ſpend moſt of their ſtrength about the periſhing comforts of this life; ſuch are the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, envious, covetous</hi> and <hi>voluptuous</hi> men and women. <hi>Moſes</hi> was fervent in Prayer, <hi>hot</hi> in the cauſe of God, but in his own, the meekeſt man on earth: his heat was not ſpent for himſelf, it was reſerved for God. Therefore our <hi>Saviour</hi> checks his Diſciples when they would pray down fire from Heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> telling them, <hi>they knew not what ſpirit they were of.</hi> In our own buſineſſe and wrongs our heat ſhould be hid, and as it were wrapt up in the embers, but when Gods honour is endangered, or obſcured, then ſhould our fire break forth, (nay, it will, if we have any) as <hi>Cyril</hi> ſometimes adviſed <hi>Theodoſius. Fourthly,</hi> They are cold in prayer, who are oppreſſed with corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or are carried away with the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſtreams of worldly cares for the preſent, (they are all choaking and quenching, as water abateth the heat of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121309:34"/> the fire;) or elſe lie under deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or a divine reſtraint, as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was often forbid, if not diſabled to pray in ſome caſes, and for ſome people. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> They that are not in charity with their neighbours. Love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the bond of perfection, and the heat of the ſoul; no love, no heat; ſo much want of heat as is want of love. <hi>Forgive, and it ſhall be forgiven; Confeſſe your f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ults one to another, and pray one for another,</hi> James 5.16. Be reconciled, then come and offer, Matth. 5.24. God will not appear to <hi>Abraham</hi> till <hi>Lot</hi> and he be agreed. <hi>Jacob</hi> being reconciled to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brother, firſt, builds an Altar. Prayer offer'd up with uncharitable hands, though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moſt excellently accompliſhed, is but as <hi>ſounding braſſe</hi> and a <hi>tinkling Cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Uſe ſerves, to adviſe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> excite and quicken you. When you pray, do it with all your might. Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter runs moſt ſwiftly and ſtrongly, when it ſwells over its own banks, and is mounted above its chanel; ſo will our ſouls move and apprehend with moſt ſtrength, when they are lifted on high and tend to God. Be not like the glow-worm,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121309:35"/> fervent in <hi>appearance</hi> onely, take you heed of <hi>Jehu</hi>'s countenance, full of fluſhing heat, and <hi>Nabals</hi> heart as cold as the ſtone. Bid defiance to <hi>Laodicean</hi> luke-warmneſſe. Remember the ſweet perfumes under the Law, were burnt before they aſcended. <hi>Hoc agite!</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on your ſelves, when you call upon God to <hi>attend</hi> you, leſt frequency di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh fervour, which ſhould encreaſe it: and cuſtome take away the ſenſe. When you are to go with a Petition to Chriſt, to be preſented to the Father, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let the minde be withdrawn from all prevalency of luſt, though from the <hi>preſence</hi> it cannot. Of worldly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, ſay as <hi>Abraham</hi> to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant with the aſſes, Stay here, while we go yonder and worſhip. Theſe Birds would rob <hi>Abraham</hi> of his Sacrifice. Call in and concenter your thoughts as men do the Sun-beams into a burning glaſſe. Have your hearts at your right hand, with <hi>Solomons</hi> wiſe man; or elſe be ſure of this, that which is upmoſt will be out ever and anon, diſtracting, dragging downward, and cooling your prayers. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Be well verſt with that Divine Rhetorick in the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121309:35"/> to move attention, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure compaſſion: Setting forth your own miſery, and uſing arguments for mercy, out of Gods own Word. God loves to be ſued on his own bond. Thus did <hi>Heſter</hi> with the King, and ſo muſt we if we will ſpeed in Heaven. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Gods own words, and ſay, (as ſhe did to <hi>Judah) Whoſe are theſe?</hi> It is acceptable to God to be preſt with his promiſe; this <hi>David</hi> knew, and therefore cries, <hi>Unite my heart to fear thy Name,</hi> Pſ. 86.11. which is as if he had ſaid, thou haſt promiſed to give me <hi>one</hi> heart, behold, I find my heart divided, my thoughts diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipated, and my ſelf diſabled for duty, <hi>(anima diſperſa ſit minor.)</hi> Unite it I beſeech thee. This is a ready way to have our prayers nigh to the Lord day and night. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Though your own Conſcience ſhould trouble and check you, though Satan labour mightily to hinder you; yea, ſay the Lord ſeem to turn away his face from you, as he did once to <hi>David,</hi> and to ſhut the door of mercy againſt you, yet faint not, <hi>cry</hi> ſtill, plead free grace, and look on <hi>Chriſt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all replies; remember who ſaith, <hi>You ſhall reap if you faint not.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:121309:36"/>
            <p>And great cauſe you have to improve your ſtrength this way: For, 1. The Lord is greatly incenſed againſt <hi>us,</hi> and <hi>others</hi> round about <hi>us;</hi> we may ſay as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſometime did in a caſe not much different, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 46. <hi>Wrath is gone out from the Lord, the plague is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun:</hi> it is a time now eſpecially, to be ſtrong in Prayer, the onely way to <hi>heal the Land,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.14. Beſides, a multitude of ſins are between God and you, and therefore great need of <hi>fervent</hi> praying; the Lord will be intreated if you be earneſt; what father ſeeing his indigent childe, though a Prodigal, on his knees, with hands lift up, with tears in his eyes, can forbear to embrace him, and to grant him his requeſt? <hi>If you who are evil know how to give good things</hi> to ſuch <hi>children, how much more will your heavenly Father give the Spirit to them that ask?</hi> 2. You may hear and ſee the poor Church of Chriſt, lying and languiſhing before you, withering in her <hi>cadency</hi> like a <hi>May-flower. Jeruſalem</hi> is become an heap of rubbiſh, our fair hopes of her eſtabliſhment almoſt blaſted, her enemies potent, and we cannot rationally conceive her ever able
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121309:36"/> to wreſtle through her difficulties; and if the Church wither, the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> cannot grow; like <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his twins, they ſmile and weep, live and die toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the children of both have cauſe to pray, if either languiſh, yea, to pray fervently for both. Surely if we have any bowels of compaſſion, we cannot hold our peace for the miſery of Zion; the Gangrene of Hereſie hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread her, more then the preſent ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on the Nation: the raging billows of prophaneneſſe is ready to overwhelm her; hell and the bottomleſſe pit are open: home-bred vipers and forrain enemies, like the <hi>children of Edom,</hi> cry out and gape for her deſtruction: ſhe is in great bitterneſſe, and is it nothing to you that paſſe by? When one of <hi>Darius</hi> King of <hi>Perſia</hi>'s <hi>Eunuchs</hi> ſaw <hi>Alexander</hi> the great ſet his feet on a low cable that had been highly prized by his maſter, he wept; and being asked the reaſon by <hi>Alexander,</hi> he anſwered, I mourn to ſee that thing my maſter ſo highly eſteemed, to be contemned, and made a foot-ſtool. What pious heart cannot bleed and weep to hear and ſee in theſe degenerate times, the deſpiſings of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121309:37"/> thoſe things which God ſo highly pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth, (Jeruſalem <hi>the perfection of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and joy of the whole earth</hi>) ſhould not this make a dumb man to ſpeak, to pray, to uſe ſtrong cries? Let every ſon of Zion conſider this. 3. You have many, and thoſe mighty enemies; <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> you, original ſin which never reſteth to draw you to evil in act; <hi>without</hi> you, Satan and his <hi>Agents,</hi> either to tempt, terrifie, or perſecute you; this ſhould make your hearts boil up in devotion. But be ſure to pray aright: Some of old cryed our (like a wind-inſtrument) loud enough on their beds, but could not be heard, and were turned off, with the cenſure of howling on their beds; like <hi>Balaam,</hi> who had words e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in his mouth, without any heat in his heart. A man may pray for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, as <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren did, and yet not be ſorry for what is paſt, nor reſolve to amend for time to come. A man may pray for power over luſt, as <hi>Auſtine</hi> confeſſeth of himſelf, and yet fear as unwilling to be heard. A man may pray for removal of judgments, and when on the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck, roar out a confeſſion, as <hi>Pharaoh, Ahab</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> did,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121309:37"/> (like the mill-wheel driven by the force of waters) and yet not think of, much leſſe be ſorry for the cauſe, and perhaps, repent of their repentance, thawing in the Sun, and freezing in the ſhade. As the Hiſtorian relates of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> that in a great ſickneſſe he vowed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, to reform his hard laws and <hi>taxes,</hi> to give ſpiritual livings free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but recovering, repented of his promiſe. And as the captivated Jews faſted and prayed for ſeventy years, but, to get off their chains, more then their ſins, and ſo like melted me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tal, held no longer then the fire laſted, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.16. <hi>They poured out prayer when thy chaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was upon them.</hi> A man may pray for grace, as <hi>Spira</hi> ſaid he did, and yet have no love to it for its excellency and beauty. All this men do, and yet not pray fervently to God. <hi>Pauci quaerunt Deum propter ſe, ſed propter aliud.</hi> He onely that is mighty in Scripture, that is mighty in the Spirit, that is mighty by Chriſt to do all things, can thus pray; <hi>O God, create in me a clean heart, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a right ſpirit within me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Theſe fervent expreſſions are not alwaies ſucceſsful; a time may
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121309:38"/> come, when a <hi>Moſes</hi> and a <hi>Samuel</hi> may not be heard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. <hi>Fervent expreſſions,</hi> though they be one and chief, yet not the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly means, ſomewhat elſe muſt be done, <hi>viz.</hi> ſubmiſſion in Petitioners, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in thoſe for whom it is peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. 2. Theſe fervent expreſſions are alwaies, <hi>Firſt,</hi> According to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine purpoſe, though not alwaies to your intents and ends. <hi>Secondly,</hi> For your ſelves and own good, though not alwaies for others; your prayers ſhall return into your own boſome. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> it may be your Petition is heard and granted, but the time of manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation is not yet come; be conſtant and wait a while, <hi>you ſhall reap. Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charies</hi> prayers for a childe were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted long before it was diſcovered to him. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Elſe you may be out in the thing deſired; either for the <hi>matter,</hi> it may not be good in it ſelf, or not for you; or not for the <hi>meaſure,</hi> not ſo much as is deſired; or for the <hi>time,</hi> it may not be good now: and then no wonder if you be not heard; which is the ſecond branch in my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Prayer, <hi>viz. Fervent expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:121309:38"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Of holy deſires.]</hi> Theſe are the feet on which the ſoul runs, the wings on which it mounts toward the object deſired.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holy</hi> they muſt be for <hi>Perſon, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, Matter</hi> and <hi>End.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Perſon</hi> muſt be <hi>holy.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law the Swan which was white in feathers, was yet reputed unclean and unmeet for ſacrifice, becauſe the skin under them was black. Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous workings ſtand in Gods account, according to the qualification of the workman, either for acceptance or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>fervent expreſſions</hi> muſt come from an <hi>holy heart:</hi> they are not the childe of wit and phantaſie, but the rapture of an elevated ſpirit, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly dew of a good heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. <hi>If I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear my prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To explain this branch, we may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire fitly,</p>
            <p>Firſt, What this <hi>holy Heart</hi> is? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, 1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> It is in Scripture diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to be a <hi>broken contrite</hi> heart, a ſelf-condemning, ſelf-crucifying, ſinne mortifying-heart. Prayer comes for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121309:39"/> mercy, and muſt bring a veſſel to hold it, and that is a <hi>broken</hi> heart; a paradox in nature but not in grace. <hi>Deus non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundit oleum miſerecordiae niſi in vas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritum;</hi> the ſacrifices of God are a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſpirit. An heart that by paſſing under the hammer of the Law, and through the melting fire of the Goſpel, is divided from the band of ſin, which is a fruit of that ſweet <hi>Spirit of grace</hi> promiſed, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10, 11, 12. <hi>The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of grace and ſupplication;</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>they ſhall look on him whom they have pierced, and they ſhall mourn for him,</hi> &amp;c. It hides nothing, like a broken veſſel, lets all run out; opens and ſpreads all its vileneſſe before the Lord: As water, mire, ſtones, heterogeneals, which were inſeparably congealed in a hard bound froſt, yet they all lie looſe when there comes a kindly thaw; ſo in the heart that was once congealed in the mire and dregs of ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and with peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall brokenneſſe is kindly thawed and diſſolved, the ſins that before ſtuck faſt in the ſoul, now lie looſe, the ſpirit longs to be rid of them all, and ſo becomes more capacious. Broken language, if from a broken heart is acceptable. 2. It
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121309:39"/> is an <hi>humble flexible</hi> heart, waiting for, and ready to receive <hi>divine</hi> impreſſions, like ſoftned wax; and as melted mettle, will run into any mould; an holy heart will be ready to bend and bow as God will have it: <hi>Acts</hi> 9.6. <hi>What wilt thou have me to do?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Lord, do but thou command me and I am ready to obey: Lord, give me ability to do what thou commandeſt, and then command me what thou pleaſeſt;</hi> as <hi>Auſtin</hi> once of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. A <hi>carnal</hi> heart waits for, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth the commands of ſin; and an <hi>holy</hi> heart waits for, and is ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the commands of Chriſt; to ſtoop to that ſervice which bears Gods ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription on it. 3. It is a <hi>chaſte, clean</hi> heart, wholly dedicated to God, that loveth no evil in motion or action; <hi>Create in me a clean heart,</hi> Pſal. 51.10. Holineſſe is a cleanſing thing 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. As a good wife is towards her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſuch is the <hi>holy</hi> heart to Chriſt; eſpouſed it is to him: The <hi>carnal</hi> heart hath <hi>many lovers,</hi> but the <hi>holy</hi> heart hath <hi>one whom it loveth, even Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.2.4. It is an <hi>heavenly</hi> heart. Words, deeds, behaviour, not onely in ſacred but in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil affairs, are <hi>heavenly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>Our converſation
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121309:40"/> is in Heaven:</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Habitually. Corpore ambulamus in terra, corde habitamus in co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> The body is on earth, but our heart in Heaven; as the pearl that grows in the Sea, but ſhines as the sky. O the preciouſneſſe of an holy heart. A perſon thus rightly qualified for prayer, is more honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>more excellent then his neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> Secondly, Why muſt Prayer come from an holy heart?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe a <hi>carnal</hi> heart deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of renewing grace and ſpiritual life, cannot riſe to cloſe with ſuch a ſpiritual duty. <hi>A natural man recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not the things of the Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14. Light and darkneſſe may as ſoon come together and agree. An <hi>holy</hi> heart may make a <hi>carnal</hi> prayer, but a <hi>carnal</hi> heart can never make an <hi>holy</hi> prayer, ſo as to aſcend high enough. Nothing can work beyond the activity of its own principle. A bullet flyeth no farther then the force of the powder carrieth it: and where prayers come from <hi>nature</hi> onely, they go no farther then <hi>nature</hi> can carry them. Secondly, <hi>Reigning ſin</hi> in the heart, out-cryeth your prayers: eſpecially the ſins of pride
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121309:40"/> and anger, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.6. <hi>God reſiſteth the proud,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.8. <hi>I will that men every where pray, lifting up holy hands without wrath.</hi> If your ſins be <hi>hearty,</hi> your prayers cannot be <hi>hearty.</hi> If the ſin of one man may hinder the prayers and endeavours of many; how much more will many ſins hinder the prayers of one. <hi>Reigning</hi> ſin is like many great Ordnance charged and planted on high mountains, they make a great noiſe; like thunder which confounds and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows up lower and ſmaller cries. Sin unto prayer is as <hi>Garlick</hi> to the <hi>Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> renders it flat and dead. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The <hi>perſon</hi> muſt be accepted before the <hi>prayer,</hi> and none are accepted but ſuch as are <hi>ſanctified</hi> by faith in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Therefore prayers muſt come from an holy heart. <hi>John</hi> 15.5. <hi>He that abideth in me bringeth forth much fruit. Gen.</hi> 4.4. The Lord had reſpect to <hi>Abel,</hi> and then to his <hi>offering.</hi> Prayer from a wicked heart, is like a jewel put into a dead mans mouth, loſeth all its vertue<note n="*" place="margin">The Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt ſaith, <hi>a precious jewel</hi> put into a dead mans mouth, loſeth its worth and vertue; ſo doth prayer in the mouth of a man ſpiritually dead.</note>. <hi>The prayer of the wicked is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:121309:41"/> Prov. 21.27. <hi>But if the tree be good, the fruit will be good.</hi> You muſt be in Chriſt before you can do or obtain any good this way. <hi>Through him we have acceſſe with confidence unto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Epheſ. 2.18. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Becauſe the Lord is holy and cannot endure ſin, eſpecially in Petitioners. God hates ſin naturally where ever it is: (like as we hate poiſon, whether it be in a <hi>Toad</hi> or Princes <hi>Cabinet.</hi>) Yea, he hateth it more then the Devil. Can a Prince en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a Petitioner that ſhall bring his greateſt enemy with him in his hand, even into his preſence? Or can any Petitioner think <hi>ſo</hi> to prevail. No: As in a wound the plaiſter prevails not whileſt the iron remains within, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can prayer while ſin rankleth. God will not hear a good motion from a bad mouth. He will <hi>hide his eyes</hi> while <hi>your hands are full of blood.</hi> You love my profeſt enemies more then me, will God ſay, your boſome ſins above your requeſts. Therefore go and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, put away your ſins, and then come and offer. Thus much for the firſt branch, the <hi>Perſon</hi> muſt be holy. Again,</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:121309:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Principle</hi> muſt be <hi>holy.</hi> Your deſires muſt be the iſſues of <hi>grace,</hi> dictated by the Spirit of <hi>Christ;</hi> we know not how or what to ask without his aſſiſtance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15, 26.</p>
            <p>Here alſo may be profitably enquired two things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Why our prayer muſt come <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> from a ſpiritual principle?</p>
            <p>The Reaſons will appear to be ſuch as theſe; 1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Becauſe it is directed to the <hi>Father of Spirits,</hi> who is delighted with <hi>ſpiritual</hi> ſervice, and accepts no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this kind from men, but what comes from a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> principle. It is therefore we hear the Apoſtle enjoining prayer in the <hi>ſpirit, Epheſ.</hi> 6.18. and praying in the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Jude <hi>v.</hi> 20. This is the wind muſt ſet you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mill on work: and the poiſe that ſhould cauſe your clock to ſtrike. 2. It is to <hi>diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh</hi> prayers, <hi>First,</hi> Becauſe many prayers are but <hi>natural deſires,</hi> or hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical expreſſions of counterfeit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. The Ravens call upon God, and ſome we read of, did howl on their beds, and were importunate for corn, wine and oil, but from a <hi>natural princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> which as the Graſhopper, hope
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121309:42"/> not much above the earth, and as a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour exhaled by the Sun doth ſoon fall down again; when <hi>ſelf</hi> doth ſeek and is ſought for, as the people did <hi>Chriſt</hi> for the <hi>loaves,</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> for the purſe. And this not onely in carnal perſons, I mean ſuch as for the preſent are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of actual grace, and the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of holineſſe: but even in the regenerate. <hi>Moſes</hi> his prayer was very earneſt to enter <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>naan,</hi> and yet it was but a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deſire. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe men living under the means of grace, may go far by their <hi>own ſpirits;</hi> as, to read, repeat Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and frame prayers very exactly, as if they were full of <hi>ſpiritual life</hi> and <hi>heat.</hi> We know great wants may and do produce earneſt entreaties; terrours of God, and frights of Conſcience may make men fervent: they may deſire pardon, and removal of judgments, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited, inflicted, or threatned; nay, they may pray for grace when they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heartily deſire it, becauſe they look upon it as a means of ſafety, (as a Bridge to help them to Heaven) not becauſe they love and deſire ſanctity, and ſo all this while may be deſtitute of a gracious principle.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:121309:42"/>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Secondly,</hi> We may farther <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> enquire how prayers coming from the <hi>Spirit</hi> may be diſcerned?</p>
            <p>The Anſwer may be thus, 1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> By that <hi>liberty, light</hi> and <hi>heat</hi> following the preſence of that Spirit. (See <hi>Luke</hi> 2.25. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17.) <hi>Light</hi> to diſcern what to ask, <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>heat</hi> to order and ſend up your Petitions. It removeth impediments, freeth from the inviſible chains of the Kingdome of darkneſſe, enlargeth the heart, and helpeth to pray with fervency, ſuch <hi>ſighs and groans as cannot be uttered.</hi> 2. By an hearty, free and full <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> of our ſelves and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts to the God of prayer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, for the matter and meaſure. <hi>Not my will, but thy will be done.</hi> As <hi>Heſter</hi> ſubmitted to the good pleaſure of the King in her requeſts. And as the mother of Chriſt doth not over earneſtly in words preſſe him to do that ſhe deſired, but onely laies open the caſe, <hi>they have no wine,</hi> referring all to his diſcretion. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of <hi>Socrates,</hi> that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aught his Scholars to ask no more of God but this, <hi>that he would do them good:</hi> but how, and how much, they would leave that to him, as beſt underſtanding what is
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121309:43"/> beſt and fitteſt for us. It comes not from the <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> to drive men upon <hi>inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> with God. 3. By a patient <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation</hi> in the <hi>uſe of all other means,</hi> till the Lord be pleaſed to manifeſt his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e gracious return. This diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition flows from faith. He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth ſhall not make haſte, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.16. As the husbandman waiteth for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious fruits of the earth, and waits pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, by a natural faith he ſeeth the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in the ſeed, and ſo bears up himſelf by that faith in expectation of an harveſt. So much more doth a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual faith enable ſouls to do much more; waiting is nothing elſe but faith ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out into patience. 4. By ſpiritual cheerfulneſſe after prayer, with care to improve and apply all you get by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſome ſpiritual ends, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Hannah</hi> prayed for a ſon, and went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>and was no more ſad,</hi> and after, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated her <hi>Samuel</hi> to the ſervice of God. Thus the <hi>principle</hi> muſt be <hi>holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Deſires</hi> muſt be holy for the <hi>matter</hi> of them. [<hi>Whoſoever ſhall ask any thing according to his will believing,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.14.] And that 1. In the <hi>ground:</hi> You muſt have a promiſe for
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121309:43"/> what you ask, in particular, or at leaſt in general, diſtinctly apprehended, and rightly applied; no way repugnant to the <hi>Analogy</hi> of faith, nor to any paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Divine</hi> Providence; otherwiſe we can have no hope to be heard; For, no faculty can or ought to extend it ſelf beyond its adequate and proper object: it is limited by peculiar rules. He that prayeth without a promiſe, denieth his own requeſt. <hi>To make our fancy the higheſt rule is a preſumptuous folly: and to ask according to our own luſts, is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit blaſphemy.</hi> 2. Prayer muſt be <hi>holy</hi> in the <hi>matter,</hi> this muſt alſo bear the ſtamp of God. Whenever, your <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi> are fired, the coal muſt be taken from the <hi>Altar,</hi> nor from the <hi>Kitchin.</hi> The matter muſt be <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> or <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually</hi> deſired. For inſtance: <hi>Firſt,</hi> You may and muſt pray for the apprehenſion of Gods love, promiſed <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.4. <hi>I will love them freely. Secondly,</hi> For par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin, promiſed <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.25. <hi>I, even I am he that blotteth out thy tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſgreſſions for my own ſake, and will not remember thy ſins. Thirdly,</hi> For ſanctification of nature, promiſed <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. <hi>And the Lord thy God will circumciſe thine heart,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121309:44"/> and the heart of thy ſeed, to love the Lord thy God with all thine heart.</hi> Ezek. 36.25. <hi>Then will I ſprinkle clean water upon you, and you ſhall be clean. Fourthly,</hi> For the removal of judgments, ſpiritual or corporal, promiſed <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Call upon me in the day of trouble, and I will deliver thee,</hi> &amp;c. At leaſt for the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of them, and ſupportation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> May not we pray for temporal bleſſings?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes; As ſome men pray for ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things in a <hi>carnal</hi> way: So o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may pray for carnal bleſſings in a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> manner. Provided 1. It be done in <hi>order,</hi> and that they have their due place. Spiritual things muſt be firſt and principal, theſe ſecondary and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.33. <hi>Firſt ſeek the Kingdome of God and the righteouſneſſe thereof,</hi> &amp;c. 2. Upon condition that you <hi>ſubmit</hi> to God, both the things themſelves, and the meaſure and time. <hi>John</hi> 12.27, 28. <hi>Save me from this hour— Father glorifie thy name!</hi> It is enough to a gracious heart, if God will <hi>glorifie his own name;</hi> carnal hearts are impetuous and impatient of a check,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121309:44"/> delay, or denial: <hi>Rachel</hi> muſt have children or die. 3. With caution, that you deſire and uſe them to the Lord. Whatever you deſire for this life, make it ſerviceable towards the ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not mercies <hi>for,</hi> nor abuſe them <hi>to</hi> exceſſe, revenge, luxury. Luſt is an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt craver, but when it rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>veth any comfort, it conſumeth it in eaſe and pleaſure. This muſt be obſerved, elſe you may ask and receive not, becauſe you ask amiſſe, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.3. Your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts may not terminate in <hi>ſelf.</hi> That was but a brutiſh requeſt which we find related, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.2. <hi>Give us water that we may drink:</hi> A beaſt can aim at ſelf-preſervation. This branch of Prayer muſt have an ordination to God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly</hi> and Laſtly, <hi>Deſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> muſt be holy for the <hi>end.</hi> As may well be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from the beginning and end of the Lords Prayer; the beginning is, <hi>Hallowed be thy Name:</hi> the end is, <hi>For thine is the Kingdome, Power and Glory, for ever!</hi> As the ſuperiour Orb carries all the inferiour about with i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: So muſt this great and noble end wheel about all our deſires, and, though loweſt actions.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:121309:45"/>
            <p>Enquire we may for the clearing of this laſt branch after two things. Firſt, <hi>When is a mans end holy?</hi> Secondly, <hi>Why our ends muſt be holy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> For the firſt, When is a mans end holy?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> The Anſwer ſhall lie in theſe two things: 1. When neither <hi>himſelf,</hi> nor any other <hi>creature</hi> is the laſt end of a mans prayer: For <hi>either</hi> of them make it eccentrick, irregular. The motion muſt needs be lame, when a man ſhall make God a meer ſervant to himſelf, and move wholly on a private center of his own: and is viſibly for God, but underhand for himſelf. The Phariſees were glorious in prayer, but what they did was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by others. The Spring was not Gods grace, and the end was not Gods glory. Glorious actions without holy and pure ends, are like ſweet herbs on a noiſome dunghi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l. 2. When God is the <hi>end (ultimus,</hi> though not <hi>proximus</hi>) laſt, though not the very next or imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate end of our deſires: As in <hi>Jacobs,</hi> and <hi>Hannahs</hi> prayer, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.11. When men aim at his glory, the enl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of Chriſts Kingdome, and reſolve
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121309:45"/> what they get in prayer to ſpend for God, and the good of his <hi>Relations,</hi> with the ſanctification and ſalvation of their ſouls: then the end is holy. The want of this, was that did ſo diſcolour the (otherwiſe) excellent works of the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> which are almoſt incredible, they looked not to God in their great ſervices and brave exploits. So that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were good <hi>Bullion</hi> (as one ſpeaks) but carried not a good ſtamp upon them, and therefore would not paſſe with God. So that it is well maintained by our <hi>Divines,</hi> yea, ſome of the <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> that their works were not <hi>morally</hi> good, becauſe though the proxime end might be good, yet they knew not the ultimate end which was Gods glory.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Why muſt our ends be holy?</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label>
            </p>
            <p>Divers Reaſons may be rendred. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Some <hi>Philoſophical,</hi> and ſome <hi>Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call.</hi> Of the <hi>firſt,</hi> I will mention theſe three, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Becauſe every operative intellect doth begin with the end; that is <hi>firſt</hi> in intention, and that which doth both move the <hi>agent</hi> and denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the <hi>action.</hi> Which appeareth to be truth from two reaſons. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the end ſupplieth the room and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121309:46"/> place of the <hi>form,</hi> in all thoſe agents and acts whoſe eſſential perfection conſiſts in operation. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe the laſt end doth perfect both the <hi>actor</hi> and the <hi>action;</hi> juſtly therefore doth it begin with the end, and take denomination from the end. 2. The end muſt be holy, becauſe the laſt end eſpecially doth give beauty and amability to all the means conducing thereunto: and becauſe the appetite is terminated and quieted in the laſt end. Needs muſt his deſires be holy whoſe end is holy. 3. Becauſe the end and the means leading thereunto, are proportioned and diſpoſed together; <hi>Poſito ſine ponuntur &amp; diſponuntur media omnia, &amp;c.</hi> if a mans end be not holy, the means leading thereunto cannot be holy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> ſort of Reaſons are <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical,</hi> I ſhall give theſe two; <hi>viz. Firſt,</hi> Becauſe the Lord looks mainly to the end, and ſpecially no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es wherefore we pray. He regards not ſo much the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetick</hi> of Prayers, how numerous they are: nor the <hi>Rhetorick</hi> of them, how neat they are: nor their <hi>Geometry,</hi> how long they are; not ſo much their <hi>Muſick,</hi> how melodious, nor their
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121309:46"/> 
               <hi>Logick,</hi> how methodical; but their <hi>Divinity,</hi> how <hi>heart-ſprung</hi> they are, how they tend to his glory, how much <hi>holineſſe</hi> is twiſted about them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The end if it be holy, will ſtrengthen the Petitioner to pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſevere in the uſe of all good means. When a man with a free Conſcience can ſay, Lord, thou knoweſt my ends, they are not meerly <hi>ſelf,</hi> nor biaſſed with car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal intereſts, but holy and ſpiritual, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the beſt of my knowledge and power, (as did <hi>Hezekiah, I have walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and have done th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t which is good in thy ſight</hi>) is a good ground to reſt faith upon, for a gracious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſwer in due time.</p>
            <p>This may be uſeful to us all, by way <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> of correction and inſtruction. <hi>Firſt,</hi> For correction: there be many among us that pray, at leaſt that read or ſay prayers, (like the Parrot at <hi>Rome,</hi> that could repeat the whole Creed.) but very few that ſend up fervent expreſſions of holy deſires. Some know no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what it is to pray, they cannot diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>oro</hi> and <hi>credo.</hi> Others think not of it, that they are going into Heaven,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121309:47"/> into the <hi>Preſence-Chamber,</hi> before the Throne of a <hi>great</hi> and glorious God, when they do pray. And too many there are who reſt on the work done, <hi>numbring</hi> rather then <hi>weighing</hi> their prayers. So it cometh to paſſe, that moſt are indiſpoſed for this holy exerciſe, in all or ſome of theſe following caſes; 1. If your hearts be impure; which may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by your <hi>thoughts,</hi> now good, and then bad, and both diſregarded; by your <hi>words,</hi> the very off-ſpring of the heart, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.34. falſe, corrupt imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; by your <hi>companions</hi> choſen for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timacy, and that you moſt delight in; and by your life, if that be <hi>impure,</hi> through the reign of any one ſin: <hi>You regard iniquity in your heart, and the Lord will not hear.</hi> But obſerve, there is a two-fold impurity, one in the <hi>dominion,</hi> another from the inheſion of ſin, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the firſt here. 2. If you have and bring nothing but natural deſires, (ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient knowledge, a good memory, a quick invention, and eaſie elocution) ſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t your praying is nothing but a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er of wit and parts, rather for <hi>oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> then <hi>devotion;</hi> which may be thus diſcerned, <hi>Firſt,</hi> If your heads are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121309:47"/> then your hearts, you have more <hi>abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> then <hi>will,</hi> to do good and glorifie God. <hi>Secondly,</hi> By ſuch prayers the head may be better'd but not the heart. It is a clear caſe, the more any man prayeth ſpiritually, the more is Gods image renewed in his heart and ſoul, the heart is more benefited then the head. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If the matter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of your prayers be carnal; as, if you ſhould crave bleſſings of the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hand only, for corn, wine and oil, meat that periſheth, the <hi>bona ſcabelli,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd not <hi>throni,</hi> as <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeaketh; o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould ask theſe things in the firſt plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: the matter and manner is then carnal. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> if your ends be evil which move you to pray; and may be known from theſe three companions, F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſt, <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,</hi> when men neither o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it the duty wholly, nor go through with it, in an hearty and chearful performance. Secondly, <hi>Vain-glory,</hi> praying to be heard and praiſed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.5. A thing hateful among Heathens. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly</hi> taxed <hi>Gracchus</hi> for this, that he referr'd all his actions, not to the rule o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vertue, but to the favour of the people, that he might have their eſteem and applauſe.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121309:48"/> And as <hi>Pliny</hi> telleth, the Nightingale ſingeth far longer and ſweeter, when men are by, then at other times. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Self-love,</hi> which keeps men at home to look only or chiefly to their own good. If thus you pray, ſee what follows; Your outward groſſe ſins are daily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, by this addition of ſpiritual ſins. An unprepared, irreverent Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner takes Gods <hi>Name in vain.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, your pains and labour upon the matter are loſt, the Lord will not heat ſuch prayers; the grunting of Hogs in the ſtye, ſaith <hi>Hierom,</hi> is as pleaſing to God, becauſe he expects no more then he hath given or offered.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> The ſecond Uſe is for Inſtruction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 1. Know then, <hi>every</hi> kind of praying will not ſerve the turn. Every ſound is not Muſick. The followers of <hi>Baa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> called on his name from <hi>morning even until noon, but there was no voice, nor any thing that anſwered,</hi> 1 Kings 26.28. <hi>Yea, and they cryed aloud, and cut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r their manner,</hi> &amp;c. and no voice, nor any to anſwer, &amp;c. Papiſts ſay over abundance of compoſures which they call <hi>prayers,</hi> in ſo much as they need beads to help them keep nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121309:48"/> yet Saint <hi>James</hi> his Praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is to be deſired among them. So too many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves, who reſt on the Idol <hi>opus operatum,</hi> or, work wrought. If they be frequent in ſome common forms, they think themſelves <hi>boon-Chriſtians,</hi> though they do nothing leſſe then pray. Take heed of this, <hi>God is in Heaven and thou on earth, Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et your expreſſions be heated with reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency. 2. Learn the <hi>Art of Praying.</hi> He is a good Chriſtian that can pray well, not contenting himſelf with the <hi>form</hi> without the <hi>power.</hi> My Brethren! It is not the labour of the lips, but the travel of the heart. Common beggary is the <hi>eaſieſt</hi> and <hi>pooreſt</hi> trade, but this beggary is the <hi>richeſt</hi> and the <hi>hardeſt.</hi> Then to the work, redeem the time. It is obſerved of the <hi>Camel,</hi> that having long travell'd through ſandy deſart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> without water, <hi>impletur cum bibendi eſt occaſio, &amp; in praeteritum &amp; in futurum:</hi> (i. e.) drinks for the time paſt, and for the time to come; ſo do you: for paſt neglects, act with more diligence; now, do for what is paſt and to come. And for your direction herein, know, that he that would pray well, muſt have, <hi>firſt, Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> conſiſting in <hi>knowledge</hi> of his own
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121309:49"/> wants, and Gods treaſury in his word and promiſes. Blind devotion cannot pleaſe God. <hi>I will pray with underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> In <hi>aſſent,</hi> not only to the <hi>verity,</hi> but alſo to the equity and <hi>congruity</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the deſire and the offer. In a <hi>fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial</hi> reſting on the fidelity of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, with reference to his own caſe. All which is ordinarily got, by <hi>hearing</hi> of the Word, and former experience of Gods goodneſſe. An humble hearer, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies a zealous Petitioner. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He muſt have <hi>flexibility,</hi> or a bending of the mind to or with the duty. He muſt not be content to be down on his knees, if his heart be not up: to have his hand in the work, if his ſoul be not alſo in it. It was the ſaying of holy <hi>Bradford,</hi> that he would never leave a duty, till he had brought his heart into the frame of the duty. He would not leave confeſſion of ſin, till his heart was broken for ſin. He would not leave Petitioning for grace, till his heart was quickned in deſire. A property of a good, honeſt, ſoft and humble heart, which is a jewel, an ornament of great price in the ſight of God. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He muſt have dignity or worth, both for compoſition and preſentation. The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121309:49"/> of Prayer to compoſe it, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal merit of Chriſt to preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it. <hi>Pray alwaies with all ſupplication in the Spirit, Epheſ.</hi> 6.18. 3. Be inſtructed: when you are about to pray, call theſe things to mind: <hi>Prayer is a fervent expreſſion of holy deſires:</hi> holy for perſon, principle, matter and end. And ſo I come to the laſt part of the deſcription, that theſe holy deſires with ſpiritual fervency, muſt be preſented</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Unto the only true God by Jeſus Chriſt.]</hi> To <hi>God</hi> only, Prayers muſt be directed, not to <hi>creatures,</hi> Angel or Saint. <hi>In every thing by prayer and ſupplication with thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, let your requeſts be made known to God,</hi> Phil. 4.6. This will be cleared with a little labour. For, firſt, he only can hear and relieve you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.11. <hi>O thou that heareſt prayers, to thee ſhall all fleſh come.</hi> Iſa. 63.16. <hi>Doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſſe thou art our Father, though</hi> Abraham <hi>be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of us, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>acknowledge us not: thou art our Father, O Lord, our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> Look as nature teacheth our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to come to their parents for every thing, and to give thanks to them; ſo grace teacheth the children of God, to cry <hi>Abba,</hi> Father, to reſort to him in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121309:50"/> every condition (as they did to <hi>Joſeph</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi>) and to praiſe him for every bleſſing. As it is one of the Royalties of the King to be petitioned unto as a common parent for grace in ſundry caſes, ſo is this a <hi>divine</hi> Royalty of God, that all fleſh ſhould come to him in their ſeveral neceſſities, abaſing themſelves in confeſſing their indignity, exalting him with whom is all fulneſſe of good things, and uncontrolable power to effect for us, whatever is good accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his own pleaſure. <hi>Secondly,</hi> For this you have a command, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Call upon me in the day of trouble.</hi> Acts 8.22. <hi>Pray God if perhaps,</hi> &amp;c. Yea, and a promiſe, <hi>Whatſoever ye ask the Father in my Name, he will give it you.</hi> And God complains of ſuch who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake <hi>the fountain of living waters, and dig to themſelves pits that can hold no water. Thirdly,</hi> We have preſidents for it. The Church directs her prayer to God, <hi>Lam.</hi> 5.1. And herein ſhe is like to <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> a ſhining and a burning light. She <hi>ſhines</hi> as knowing the rich ſtorehouſe where, in her exigence to fetch relief, and ſhe goes to none below God. She <hi>burns,</hi> the fire of her zeal is kindled in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121309:50"/> her breaſt, and therefore goes not with cold, luke-warm affections. In that Prayer our <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> taught his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, we are taught the ſame; Look over the form, obſerve the phraſes, and ſee whether you can imagine, that <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> ſhould ever be directed to any other. Read through all the Records of the world, and ſhew if you can, where any Saint of God made ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ica ion unto any but to God only! You cannot; no, not to the <hi>Virgin</hi> the Mother of Chriſt, nor to any other Saint or Angel. And in all the preſidents recorded in the ſacred Scriptures, not only in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (while the <hi>Fathers</hi> are fondly ſuppoſed to be in <hi>Limbo,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> gives the reaſon why we do not then read of any praying to Saints.) but in the New, after our Saviours aſcenſion. And if there be neither command, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe nor preſident in the <hi>Old</hi> or <hi>New Teſtament</hi> for invocation of Saints, is it not a wonder, it hath been ſo much preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and practiſed. To the contrary we have, <hi>viz. Matth.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10.22.9. Alas all other perſons are rather praying to God, then to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, as God. God is the authour of every
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121309:51"/> perfect gift, and to ſeek it from any other is flat idolatry; and to give the praiſe thereof to any but God, is ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>Further we add, <hi>By and through Jeſus Chriſt.]</hi> We cannot mount to Heaven on our own wings: nor reach God by our own ſtrength: as ſoon may we ſcale Heaven with ladders. And beſides, how terrible and horrible is it to <hi>think</hi> of God, much more to <hi>come</hi> to him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt. The holineſſe and juſtice of God were before Chriſt as two flaming ſwords to keep off ſouls from coming to him: but <hi>by Chriſt,</hi> they both look on the ſoul with a lovely and aimable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. And, whatever you ask the Father in Chriſts name, believing, ye ſhall receive.</p>
            <p>For the farther benefit of Practitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in this <hi>holy Art,</hi> here will be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, 1. What it is to offer up Prayers by Chriſt? 2. <hi>Why they muſt be ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> What is it to offer up Prayers by Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer: 1. It is to have them <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed</hi> by the Spirit of Chriſt. I name this the oftner, leſt you ſhould truſt to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121309:51"/> your own ſpirits, &amp; content your ſelves with meer <hi>natural deſires.</hi> And further to move you, both to prize and to procure and cheriſh the <hi>ſpirit of prayer.</hi> 2. It is to direct Prayers <hi>to</hi> Chriſt, aſcending by his glorious <hi>humanity</hi> towards the <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that ſo the gift may be ſanctified by the <hi>Altar.</hi> It is Chriſts office <hi>to pray the Father</hi> for his Saints, and it is their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to call upon him ſo to do, and direct their holy deſires to him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.16. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is to have Prayers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by Chriſt to the Father, and taken as immediately from him, who is heard in all his ſuits. <hi>John</hi> 11.42. <hi>I know that thou heareſt me alwaies.</hi> This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to offer up Prayers by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Why muſt Prayers be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> up by him?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer: 1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Becauſe of the <hi>Covenant</hi> is made with him; all the <hi>promiſes are in him yea!</hi> Yea, indeed, all the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are made to him firſt, and by him to us. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. He is called the <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the Covenant.</hi> No intercourſe now between God and man, but by and through him. The keys of the houſe of <hi>David</hi> are laid on his ſhoulders. He is the only door, and through him we
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121309:52"/> have <hi>boldneſſe of acceſſe to the Father:</hi> and confidence to enter into the Holieſt, <hi>by the blood of Jeſus,</hi> by <hi>a new and living way,</hi> Heb. 10.20. 2. He is both the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Altar</hi> for his Church. No o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prieſts or Altars now properly but Chriſt: Since <hi>Prieſt, Altar</hi> and <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> met in one, in him. No more <hi>Prieſts, Altars</hi> or <hi>Sacrifices</hi> but Metaphorical. As then, all Sacrifices were to be brought to the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and offered on the <hi>Altar</hi> appointed, ſo it muſt be now. We have an <hi>Altar</hi> upon which all our ſpiritual Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices muſt be offer'd, even the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> Heb. 13.10. If we go and offer without him, <hi>the Altar,</hi> and in our own name, the ſacrifice will be loathed. It is not becauſe we perform a duty in the moſt excellent manner, that it is accepted, but becauſe Chriſt our <hi>high-Prieſt</hi> preſents both us and our performances to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So that if a man ſhould offer as many Sacrifices as were at the dedication of <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, and all without ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, and that all the qualifications did meet in the perſon that did offer: yet all theſe are accurſed, if offer'd in their own name. As the leaſt things that were offer'd, even an <hi>Epha,</hi> or a <hi>Gomer,</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:121309:52"/> a pair of <hi>Turtle Doves,</hi> or a <hi>mite,</hi> were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted from the hand of the <hi>high-Prieſt,</hi> when rivers of oil ſhould be refuſed, if preſented otherwaies. We muſt do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this caſe, as the Country of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> having need of <hi>Herods</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, made ſuit to <hi>Blaſtus</hi> his Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, that was gracious with him. And as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> being to make a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> took with him young <hi>Alexander, Philips</hi> belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſon. We can then hope to ſpeed with God, when by faith we take <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> with us to be our Interceſſour, to preſent and offer our prayers to God. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>beſt</hi> prayers of the Saints here, as they proceed from men, are <hi>tainted</hi> and unſavoury; yea, to go far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the moſt gracious actions which they are enabled to do by <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> are coming through them ſo imperfect, (as pure water running through a foul pipe, getteth ſome ſoil upon it: and excellent generous wine will taſte of the cask, if it be not ſweet.) ſo vitiated, as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very unfit for the Lords holy and pure preſence. And therefore we read of the <hi>ſmoak of the incenſe</hi> coming with the prayers of the Saints. They muſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121309:53"/> be dipped in his blood, perfumed with his odours, otherwiſe they will ſtink worſe in Gods noſtrils, then ever did the Onions and Garlick of <hi>Egypt.</hi> It was the fault of King <hi>Uzziah</hi> to burn incenſe upon the <hi>Altar</hi> without a <hi>Prieſt:</hi> he was reſiſted by eighty valiant Prieſts of the Lord, and ſtruck with Leproſie, to make you fear to do the like, by offering up prayers to God without Chriſt. The work cannot be accepted, where the perſon is not: and the perſon is accepted in and for Chriſt's ſake.</p>
            <p>Now ſtand ſtill, look back, lay all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and conclude two things, by way of Application.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The miſery of graceleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (though indowed with many natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall abilities) in that they cannot pray, in beſt health and proſperity, much leſſe in ſickneſſe and danger. They have no ability, skill nor will to pray with any power and life. The Painter can give external lineaments and outward repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, but he cannot give that which is the <hi>actus primus,</hi> life to them; the hypocrite may give outward colours and ſhades, but he wants this <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> As the Satyre in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121309:53"/> ſtrove to make a dead man ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, but could not, ſaid, <hi>Deeſt aliquid intus:</hi> there wants a principle within to enable him to ſtand. So may we ſay, the carnal man that praies, wants a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple within to put forth ſpiritual prayer. He is that like a ſhip that is wind-bound. No ſtirring without the <hi>Spirits</hi> gales. There is great difference between <hi>praying</hi> and <hi>reading</hi> or ſaying over a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; theſe have no <hi>fervent expreſſions,</hi> their heat goeth another way; no <hi>holy deſires</hi> can come from ſuch impure, proud, prophane ſpirits; either they go to the creature as the end, or by the creature as the mean, and what ſucceſſe can be expected? That's a true rule: <hi>Bonum eſt ex integris cauſis, malum è quolibet defectu:</hi> Good, like harmonious Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, if one ſtring jar, the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmony is marred; and like beauty which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated of the Symmetry of parts, if one part be deformed, the beauty is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated; thus it is in any good action, let it be never ſo admirable for the matter of it, if there be any failing or crack in the <hi>principle, manner</hi> or <hi>end,</hi> the man lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the comfort and the reward of the duty. <hi>You ask and have not, becauſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121309:54"/> you ask amiſſe.</hi> Let ſuch conſider two things: <hi>Firſt,</hi> That all their hope, ſuch as it is, themſelves confeſſing, is upon their prayers, good meaning and good deeds; now, without grace and Chriſts Spirit, you can do none of theſe; (he that wants the <hi>Spirit of Grace,</hi> muſt needs be deſtitute of the <hi>Spirit of Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi>) You hope to be ſaved by your good prayers, and cannot pray: by your good deeds, and can do none: without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God. In what condition are you then? <hi>Secondly,</hi> None can ſtead you but God; not friend, not wit, not wealth, were you ſet as the <hi>Caliph</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> once was in the midſt of a golden treaſure, and yet ſtarved: in the midſt of all theſe and cannot pray, in what a miſerable caſe are you? <hi>The dead pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe not God, they that are in the pit call not upon him:</hi> and without prayer no good thing can be had.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let all learn their <hi>duty,</hi> to amend your praying; elſe, you may <hi>howl upon your beds,</hi> and call loud upon him, and not be heard. It is not ſpeaking or babling, but praying that hath the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. See where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121309:54"/> you have been faulty, apprehend and acknowledge it; for time to come, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not, meaſure not the length of your prayers, <hi>weigh</hi> them in Chriſts ballance, <hi>viz.</hi> by the <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>holineſſe</hi> of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, by the merit of Chriſt, and by the reverent <hi>fervency of expreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus from the deſcription of <hi>fervent-working prayer,</hi> I proceed to <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, Caſes, Conditions</hi> and <hi>Motives;</hi> ſo to cloſe this Doctrine. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label>
            </p>
            <p>It may be objected, <hi>firſt, What need of this ado?</hi> Will not leſſe pains ſerve the turn? God knows our wants already, he will do what ſeemeth good in his ſight. His Decrees are immutable, and cannot be alter'd by all our e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rneſtneſſe and endeavours.</p>
            <p>Thus indeed argued <hi>Maximus Tyrius</hi> an Heathen. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> And thus many <hi>Libertines</hi> in our daies. But to the Anſwer. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is not for Gods <hi>information,</hi> but the creatures <hi>ſubmiſſion,</hi> we pray for his leave; yea, when he will do any thing, he ſtirreth up thoſe that are his to deſire that which otherwiſe he would have done, to the intent that for <hi>honours</hi> ſake, he might attribute the ſame unto their prayers. Beſides, Gods <hi>Decrees</hi> do not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121309:55"/> exclude the duty of the creature, and the work of ſecond cauſes, <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11, 12. <hi>I know the thoughts of peace I have toward you, yet yee ſhall call upon me, and I will hear you.</hi> This, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> knew, and the former, turned Gods predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the latter, his promiſes into prayers. Finally, We pray not in any caſe to the intent that God ſhould be changed, which thing ſhould be attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted in vain: for he is immutable; but rather, that we our ſelves ſhould be changed, for ſo much as in praying we are made capable of the divine benefits. By vertue of Gods Ordination, a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual holy prayer caſteth the ſoul into a better diſpoſition, ſo that now he is made capable of ſpiritual bleſſings, which before it was not. So that we draw not God neerer to us by our arguments, but we draw neerer unto him.</p>
            <p n="2"> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> 2. Some ſay they cannot pray, or at leaſt not according to that deſcription of Prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> I Anſwer, 1. If you cannot pray at all, then you are <hi>ſpiritually</hi> dead. The blinde man may juſtly ſay, he <hi>cannot ſee,</hi> the deaf man, that he <hi>cannot hear,</hi> the ſame man, that he <hi>cannot go:</hi> but
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121309:55"/> 
               <hi>nemo vivens poteſt dicere, non poſſum ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi> No <hi>living</hi> man can ſay, cannot pray. The blinde, the lame, the deaf, if they have any grace, any jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> life, may pray: <hi>the dead only praiſe thee not, O Lord!</hi> Neither can any man pray acceptably without <hi>the Spirit.</hi> 2. It is true, you cannot pray of your ſelves, by <hi>natural</hi> abilities, or any <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> principle. <hi>Pray</hi> that you may pray, for you know not what you ſhould pray for, as you ought, <hi>but the Spirit helpeth your infirmities.</hi> As a poor hungry man craves an alms, or a condemned priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner a pardon, ſo, humbly and earneſtly ſeek of God, the aſſiſtance of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit, the Spirit of Prayer, eying what is written for your comfort, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. <hi>If you being evil know how to give good gifts unto your children: how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give the Spirit to them that ask.</hi> 3. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir</hi> up thoſe gifts and abilities connatural and acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whatever they be, though never ſo few or weak, and do what you can with them. If you can but look up and ſigh out your wants, and with ſilent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the heart (where words and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther skill is wanting) ſend up your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121309:56"/> to Heaven. The <hi>Ravens</hi> call upon the Lord, he hears and feeds them: you are better in Gods eſteem then <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</hi> 4. By timely and ſtirring endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, remove the impediments of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. As are ignorance, pride, diſtraction, through variety of evil motions, or earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly employments, difuſe and the like; Theſe clip the wings of the ſoul, and are to it as <hi>lead</hi> to the net, bear it down; they are the <hi>ruſt</hi> of the ſoul and do mightily ſtreighten and render it uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. Many complain of power, when will is wanting. They ſay they cannot do this or that, when through ſpiritual ſloth they never tried. 5. Hear and join ſometimes as conveniently you may, with ſuch as can pray fervently. Thoſe that have any ſparks of heavenly fire in their breaſts, may be a means to inflame others, as a dead coal catcheth fire being caſt among living coals: and green wood taketh fire when it is laid with the dry; at leaſt to give a good <hi>preſident</hi> and great encouragement to the duty. I heartily wiſh you knew the benefit of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. The communion of Saints is the <hi>perfection of beauty and joy of the whole earth;</hi> No better help to Prayer then
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:121309:56"/> the ſociety of thoſe who can and do pray with frequent fervency. Eſpecially be careful to note your enemies which go about, yea, often hinder you from this duty. And they are ſuch as theſe <hi>viz. Firſt,</hi> Your <hi>ſleighting</hi> of the duty, that it is an eaſie thing to pray. And ſo it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as moſt go about it, not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing between reading and ſaying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a prayer, and <hi>prayer</hi> indeed. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, men, yea, good men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men put not their ſtrength to it, but haſtily run over it as a task; inſomuch that frequency doth allay fervency, and cuſtome doth turn prayer into a fruitleſs formality, indeed, vain babling. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> Living in ſome <hi>ſecret ſin,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, <hi>pride,</hi> (God reſiſteth the proud,) and enmity with your neighbours. This is one of the worſt ſigns in the world, eſpecially to be out with the people of God. Yet ſuch broils Satan laboureth to foment, and chiefly for this end, to <hi>hinder prayers,</hi> or to ſlack the fervency of them, if he can, between man and wife, Miniſter and people; the Devil well knows, guilt to be a tongue-tying thing; Great ſins to be great gags. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> on this account prays, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.14, 15.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121309:57"/> 
               <hi>Deliver me from bloods, O Lord, then my tongue ſhall ſing aloud of thy righteouſneſſe: Open my mouth!</hi> Guilt had put a padlock on <hi>Davids</hi> mouth, and he could not ſpeak to God, whom he had ſo much offended. Sin approved, makes the Lord deaf, and the ſinner dumb. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Variety of <hi>worldly</hi> buſineſſe and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of oppreſſing cares; theſe are the birds that would rob <hi>Abraham</hi> of his Sacrifice, and ſwarms of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which annoy the beſt; coming <hi>neceſſarily,</hi> they prove a cumber, but when men <hi>volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily</hi> thruſt themſelves upon, and delight to be in them, as a fiſh in water, they choak the ſeed, and thruſt duty out of doors, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.22. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34. Oh how quickly will theſe thorns overtop the corn! <hi>Fourthly, Satan</hi> and <hi>wicked</hi> company, which unlooſe a man, and diſreliſh ſpiritual employments, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to caſt a beclouding miſt upon the bleſſed <hi>beauty of holineſſe,</hi> and to vail the ſpiritualneſſe of this exerciſe from the eye of the minde. Either they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſe men wholly and keep them off from it, as forgetful or fearful to come into Gods preſence; or elſe, to keep them contented with a meer form; ſo
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121309:57"/> that men may go to Hell praying in that manner, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 7.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But many that have uſed thus to <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>3</label> be fervent in praying, as you now teach, have afterwards proved counterfeits? <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Will you therefore diſlike it, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> and not pray fervently at all? Suppoſe ſome <hi>coin</hi> be counterfeit, will you therefore keep no ſilver in your purſe? I think you will not ſo eaſily be perſwaded: Some abuſe good callings, will you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore caſt off all? How can tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Religion, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is a kinde of madneſſe in civil matters? If an abuſe of ſome ſhould merit an aboliſhment of all good things of that natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, what would have become of us by this time? But to anſwer more punctually. <hi>Firſt,</hi> All thoſe have not proved counterfeits, that have been thus <hi>fervent in prayer.</hi> God forbid, that you ſhould ſo think. <hi>Moſes, Joſhuah, David, Hannah, Daniel, Paul,</hi> with many hundreds of bleſſed ſouls, have held out in a growing fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency, and proved beſt at laſt. <hi>Secondly,</hi> In thoſe that have falen, the fault was not in their fervent praying, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of Religion, but their <hi>falſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121309:58"/> hearts,</hi> blame <hi>unſoundneſſe</hi> only, and give <hi>zeal,</hi> her due praiſe. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Let their example make you affraid, of any, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, <hi>ſelf-deceiving-hypocriſie.</hi> Keep truth in the inward parts. Labour <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> for ſincerity. Let the greateſt heat be inward, in the intention of the ſpirit this way. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Regard not ſo much what the <hi>common</hi> ſort ſay, as what <hi>God</hi> and your need requires. If others deride it, the <hi>Scriptures</hi> commend it. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Joſhuah;</hi> let all others do and be what they pleaſe, go you and pray fervently, with all your ſtrength. It is ſad to ſee, how careleſſe, indevout, cold and irreverent the generality of people are amongſt us! if by their publick we may judge of their private devotion. Mend this, and the reſt of your ſpiritual maladies will be eaſily cured.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>4</label> But many we ſee have bleſſings of all ſorts, who yet never could, nor did pray thus for them; there appears then no ſuch neceſſity of <hi>fervency in prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> You muſt diſtinguiſh of bleſſings, and then anſwer your ſelves. 1. For the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of them, they are alwaies bleſſings, either of <hi>common Providence,</hi> or of <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all favour</hi> and <hi>promiſe.</hi> The former are
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121309:58"/> and may be enjoyed without any prayer, and therefore without fervency, coming from God as a <hi>Creatour,</hi> to ſupport his creature in being, till the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ordained end be obtained. The latter, which are bleſſings indeed, ſweet, full and laſting, muſt be ſued out with ſtrong cries, and fervency of devotion. <hi>I will yet for this be enquired of by the houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>to do it for them,</hi> Ezek. 36.37. Many rich favours promiſed in the former verſes, but they muſt be fetcht by Prayer. 2. For the <hi>end</hi> of them, ſome are beſtowed on men for their <hi>everlaſting good,</hi> as are <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving graces,</hi> and a <hi>ſanctified uſe</hi> of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon favours; effects of Prayer in <hi>adult</hi> perſons. Other bleſſings are beſtowed not ſo much for themſelves as for the good of others; Such are <hi>functional</hi> abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, for the good of humane ſocieties: as <hi>Saul</hi> called to be King had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nother heart given him, without prayer for it. 3. For the <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>continuance;</hi> that ſhews whether they be the perſons of devout Prayer or no. Men may have bleſſings with a curſe, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.11. <hi>I gave them a King in mine anger,</hi> &amp;c. as he once gave them <hi>quails</hi> to choak them. Like <hi>Achans</hi> wedge, <hi>Gehezies</hi> ſilver, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oboams</hi>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:121309:59"/> Crown, (all were gifts of God, but yet giftleſſe.) <hi>Ahabs</hi> Vineyard ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from <hi>Naboth,</hi> becauſe convenient for him. Some things are <hi>lawful,</hi> but not convenient; this was convenient, but not lawful: it had been better for him and his, had he ſuffered ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies to have enjoyed things <hi>lawful.</hi> Poſſeſſion without <hi>right,</hi> and proſperity without <hi>prayer</hi> frequent and fervent, is the bane and ruine of all.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>5</label> It is again objected, If we ſhould practiſe this duty every day, as is preſſed, it would ſpend and waſte our ſpirits, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us in our callings, and expoſe us to the deriſion of others?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> I Anſwer, 1. I have read of ſome men who have been ſomewhat hurt in their bodily health, by <hi>faſting,</hi> watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and much kneeling; [<hi>James</hi> ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the <hi>juſt,</hi> Chriſts kinſman, had his knees made as hard as Camels knees, with much praying; as <hi>Euſebius</hi> rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. <hi>Father Latimer</hi> during his impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, was ſo conſtant and frequent in prayer, that he was much impaired in his bodily ſtrength, as is related by Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> in his <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Monuments.</hi>] But I never read or heard, nor conceive
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121309:59"/> it poſſible, that ever any man was hurt by fervency in prayer. This heat, I ſpeak of, conſumeth no radical moiſture, an heavenly dew goeth with it as a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial, to cool, refreſh and make glad men in prayer. 2. I demand, Can your time and ſtrength be ſpent in a bette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> emploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? No man ſpends ſo much as he gains in prayer. You are miſtaken, and ſlander this ſweet communion with God, while you lay ſuch blame, upon ſecret or private-devotion in family-du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Doth not the ſatisfying of your luſts ſpend you? Do not evil company and riot conſume you? Doth not your neglect and backwardneſſe in <hi>ſowing (Charity</hi> is ſo called by the Apoſtle, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6.) beggar you? it is not prayer. 3. How can you after delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration account it an hinderance of you or yours in their work? <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is a matter of greateſt weight and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for comfort, credit and profit; and to matters of greateſt importance we account all other things but lets, but not <hi>them</hi> as lets to any thing of a ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate nature. If the King or ſome ſpecial Favourite ſhould come to your <hi>Place,</hi> and publiſh a will to admit any
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121309:60"/> to his preſence, that you might confer with him an hour or two, about your wrongs and wants: would you ſo plead, Alas, we have not the leaſure, it would hinder us in our callings? I trow not: but rather put off all occaſions, attend this: So judge in the <hi>Caſe</hi> now in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It doth much further you in all your worldly affairs. You know, the baiting of the horſe doth not hinder the journey, nor the whetting of the ſythe, the work, but further them. <hi>The bleſſing of the Lord maketh rich,</hi> and fervent prayer is the ſouls meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger ſent up to fetch it down, on ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, cattle, grounds, and the whole day and night. Therefore is prayer called by one of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> the <hi>lock</hi> of the night, and the <hi>key</hi> of the day: to ſhut up from harm, and to let in the Sun, even the <hi>Sun of righteouſneſſe</hi> in his glorious beams and raviſhing influence, into every ſad, dark and drooping ſoul. 4. Grant all you ſay; Suppoſe it ſome hinderance; will you be at no charge to wait upon God, and to prefer your Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to him? You can hardly expect ſo eaſie and ſuch cheap audience in any <hi>earthly Princes</hi> Court, to have your Petitions
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121309:60"/> preſented and anſwered without fees, or moving gratuities. And, will you part with nothing for <hi>God,</hi> not ſo much as hazard a pretended loſſe? <hi>David</hi> was of another minde, when called to build an <hi>Altar,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. <hi>He would not offer that to God which coſt him nothing.</hi> It is true God is not won thus, <hi>our good extends not to him;</hi> yet he would have us willing to part with all for the purchaſe of <hi>the pearl:</hi> to account all things but dung in reſpect of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him, and the fruition of Chriſt; he can give you a rich dew upon your labours much more then this, and infinitely recompence your ſuppoſed hinderance. A whet is no let, you ſay: and for all the haſte of work and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, you will have time to eat your meat, three or four times a day, that you may do your work both better and ſpeedier; O fools and unwiſe! to judge prayer a loſſe, a hinderance, while it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſheth the ſoul of poor <hi>Pilgrims,</hi> ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth edge on all our ſpiritual imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and calleth in the Lord to be and help you in your buſineſſe! Many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands now in Heaven are bleſſing God for the benefit of Prayer. No time can
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121309:61"/> be ſpent better. But I am ſenſible of a <hi>Digreſſion;</hi> my aim is to aſſure you, (my Beloved in the Lord, for whoſe ſake this is written) <hi>that Prayer is the beſt way to thrive.</hi> To ſuch as reſted on the Lords day according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, did not the Lord give a double portion of <hi>Manna</hi> the day before? And to ſuch as paid their Tythes for the maintenance of the Sanctuary, did not the Lord promiſe to <hi>open the windows of Heaven,</hi> Malac. 3.10? <hi>Abraham</hi> had this promiſe of abundance performed to him; So had <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperour, the Churches great <hi>Benefactor,</hi> ſo many temporal bleſſings, as never any man durſt to wiſh. <hi>Aug. de Civit. Dei. Laſtly,</hi> Where you men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fear of <hi>Deriſion,</hi> it is of all other the leaſt diſcouragement. If others laugh, do you mourn; if they ſcoff, do you counſel; if they curſe, do you bleſſe and pray. The beſt things do hear ill from the worſt men. <hi>They know not what they do.</hi> Let Dogs bark, or mad men ſhoot arrows to the <hi>Lights</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>they</hi> with their radiant light and motion do ſtill ſerve their Creatour. So ſay you, <hi>If this be to be vile, I will be more
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121309:61"/> vile then thus.</hi> Chuſe you, whether you will pray or no, as for me, I will pray <hi>fervently</hi> to God, who only is able to ſave us from ſin and Hell.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Objections,</hi> we proceed to ſome <hi>Caſes</hi> of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What ſhould a man do that <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Caſe </seg>1</label> cannot utter his minde, he wants fit words for ſuch a preſence?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let ſuch a one know, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> that an unfeigned <hi>fervent deſire</hi> of the heart is to God an acceptable prayer: and broken language coming from a broken heart, avails more then affectation of well-couched words, without <hi>affection</hi> of prayer. I ſay, the buſineſſe of prayer is more diſpatched by <hi>ſighs,</hi> then ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, by inward groans, more then out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward garniſhes. As the Lord heareth without ears, ſo he underſtandeth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out words. <hi>Sighs</hi> and breathing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to God are articulate. There is great diſpute among the <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> about the ſpeech of <hi>Angels:</hi> but this they agree in, that one Angel ſpeaketh thus to another, when any one hath a conceit in his minde of any thing, with a will that another ſhould underſtand it, and that <hi>God</hi> ſhould alſo, that is enough for the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121309:62"/> expreſſion of it; So it is with the ſpirit of man, in ſpeaking to God, for the ſpirit of man agreeth with Angels. Though it is our duty to ſtrive to pray in fit words, and to be enriched in all ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance and knowledge, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. Therefore 2. Let him for a time uſe the help of godly mens pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, compoſed to his hand, by the ſame Spirit, and purpoſely intended for ſuch, as want knowledge, memory or utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, till the Lord further enable the willing minde to make its requeſts known in a reverent and ſober manner, as ſavouring more of <hi>grace</hi> then <hi>art.</hi> Young beginners may finde great help in the matter, fit words, good method, from ſuch a form, and which being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to particular occaſions, do not a little quicken, revive and enlarge the heart. If you ſhould ſay, Is it lawful ſo to pray? I ſhall anſwer by asking this queſtion; Where is there any law againſt it? And where there is no law, there is no tranſgreſſion. I can finde no command againſt it. This we finde in Scripture, that <hi>Prayer</hi> is an Ordinance of God; but whether to be conceived only in the heart, or uttered by words,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121309:62"/> whether in our own, or in others words, by pronunciation or reading that is not appointed. Why then may not a godly man, and in ſome caſes eſpecially, (as when the ſoul cannot put forth its ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations) do as Chriſt did, pray oft in the ſame words to God; and that, though compoſed by another? Neither is there any thing hinders, but that a man thus doing, may pray by the Spirit; the work of the Spirit being rather 1. To teach us what graces to pray for. 2. To raiſe fervent and devout deſires after the things we pray for, <hi>(groans that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be expreſſed)</hi> then to give in words, which a man may want, and yet not want the Spirit of Prayer. Nor that I deny that the Spirit of God doth at all help, as to words and expreſſions: for he doth it <hi>mediately</hi> by ſtirring up the affections; which being raiſed, are ſome advantage to expreſſion. However we finde that through ſlowneſſe of phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, baſhfulneſſe, unreadineſſe of ſpeech, men that have good affections, may yet need forrain helps, as to words. 3. Let ſuch a one read, or hear to get by heart, ſuch paſſages of Scripture as being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly joined, will make an excellent
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121309:63"/> Prayer. It is beſt praying in the <hi>Lords</hi> own words. The <hi>Scripture</hi> is a Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine of matter. Many complain they have a great dearth of expreſſions, when the cauſe is in themſelves, they do not ſtudy the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the moſt genuine off-ſpring of expreſſions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Caſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, What ſhall he do that findes his heart <hi>unfit</hi> and altogether <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed</hi> for Prayer, eſpecially ſuch Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, with holy fervency.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> For Anſwer to this, 1. Let him conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whence that indiſpoſition is: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from ſome prevailing <hi>corruption,</hi> which muſt be mortified, or from <hi>omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of ſome <hi>duty,</hi> which muſt be bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and redeemed; or, from a tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which muſt be reſiſted; or elſe, from a deſertion, in which caſe there muſt be a waiting and earneſt ſeeking for the Lords return. 2. In this danger and damp of the ſoul, know, there is moſt need of praying to bring the heart into temper, and to free it from thoſe preſſing weights, which do ſo clog and keep it down. The only way to fit a ſoul for this duty, is to fall preſently upon it, and the very doing of the duty doth fit to the duty: As one expreſſeth it; for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121309:63"/> as all actions of the ſame kinde encreaſe the habit; ſo prayer will make ready for prayer. By ſetting a mans ſelf on the work, he ſhall gather diſpoſedneſſe, though unfit before: as joints benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, get life being uſed. 3. Know, ſuch is your condition here below: like a watch, though it be brought in order, yet ere long it will be out again: like the houſe that is ſwept, and the childes face that is waſhed, gathers duſt, and is fouled again. Yet let not this diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage you, but rather excite you to reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diligence in keeping the ſoul Heaven-ward: and like the <hi>Palm-tree,</hi> which by how much the more weight is laid upon it, gathers the more ſtrength, the more to encounter Aſſailants. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially take heed of living in any beloved ſin, and thinking to pacifie Conſcience, and ſatisfie offended Juſtice, by a task of daily prayer; a <hi>wile</hi> of Satan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eigning among Papiſts, who hearing the Maſſe, and confeſſing their ſins once a year au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly, think they may live as they liſt, and ſpend the day as they ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, as if they had taken a new licence to commit iniquity; a practice too too common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ourſelves, reſting on a cold per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121309:64"/> of ſome duties, without truth of grace, or any thought of a neceſſity of univerſal obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Caſe </seg>3</label> I am diſtracted with vain thoughts, and terrified with ſtrange fears, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly while alone and in the dark; what ſhall I do?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider whence they come; from <hi>without,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> as injections; or from <hi>within,</hi> as corruptions prevailing through <hi>negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> or meer <hi>weakneſſe;</hi> judge and ſhame thy ſelf for ſuch diſtractions, ſtrive to do better, ſo ſhall they never be imputed. To be wholly freed from them is a priviledge proper to the ſtate of perfection: as ſome diſeaſes cannot, will not be cured neer home, but men muſt repair to the <hi>Bath,</hi> or to the City for help; this <hi>infirmity</hi> is not to be quite healed, till we come to Heaven. 2. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not ſuch vain and hurtful thoughts while you are in your civil emploiments, at leaſt play not with them as children uſe to do with motes in the air; for there begins your bane: You admit them at other times, and they will be admitted at prayer. If once the minde is let looſe, to rove idly, it will hardly be brought in to attend upon God wholly in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:121309:64"/> of <hi>Prayer,</hi> or otherwiſe: as the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling fellow that wanders up and down, will not eaſily be tied to work. The beſt way to keep the heart from gadding, is to keep it as much as may be in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>une, and rightly diſpoſed before; as when a man is to uſe his horſe he will have him under bridle. 3. Though you be ſet with ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and fears, yet flie not upon ſuch imaginations, but reſiſt, and the enemy will yeeld: leave not the place where you are, but buckle ſo much the cloſer to the duty in hand. When Chriſt ſweat drops of blood, he prayed moſt fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Remember Satan is chained, he hath no enforcing power, (Diſtruſtful fear giveth advantage:) and that you are in Gods preſence, who hath power over the Devil. 4. Know, that theſe defects and diſpleaſing thoughts, do <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb</hi> and <hi>diſcomfort</hi> the praying ſoul, but cannot evacuate your prayers. This is the priviledge of a true Chriſtian, his ſpotty and defiled prayers (as other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices) are waſhed in the Foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for ſin and uncleanneſſe: he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects, interlines, and paraphraſes them, puts them into the method and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and expected conſtitution of the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:121309:65"/> Court of Heaven, that what goes from us with ſincerity is immediately taken and entred on the File, and become ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Records of that <hi>Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Caſe </seg>4</label> But I finde not any ſucceſſe in my prayers, but am rather croſſed in them: therefore I fear it is in vain to pray?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 1. If you pray amiſſe, for <hi>matter, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> or <hi>end,</hi> no <hi>marvail;</hi> in the <hi>matter,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> in his deſire to enter into the promiſed Land; the <hi>matter</hi> of prayer being temporal, we have no abſolute promiſe to obtain; Spiritual mercies indeed are <hi>bona abſoluta, &amp; bona bonum habentem facientia,</hi> ever good to him that hath them, and therefore we have an abſolute promiſe to ſpeed in our requeſts for them; <hi>he will never deny good things to them that ask,</hi> Luke 11.13. But out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſſings, are onely <hi>bona reſpectiva,</hi> good in reference to a certain end, and our expectations may fail with reference to them. In the <hi>manner;</hi> as the Church in the <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.3. She would and ſhe would not. There is it may be a kinde of wambling willingneſſe and velleitie, but it boils not up to a full height of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</hi> for God, and utmoſt endeavours after the thing deſired. Now, affection
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:121309:65"/> without endeavour, is like <hi>Rachel,</hi> beautiful, but barren. Or, Laſtly, Your prayers may miſſe in the <hi>end,</hi> either of <hi>intention</hi> or of duration. They draw not neer him with <hi>true heart,</hi> that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented either to wait for, or to want the thing deſired, being heartily willing that God ſhould be glorified, though themſelves be not anſwered. They that ask aright may have any thing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6. 2. Prayers may be ſucceſſeful and yet not found or felt. The grant may be paſt, and you not know it, for it is made to Chriſt <hi>firſt,</hi> who by the worth of his Interceſſion merits a return of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to <hi>himſelf,</hi> and after to his Saints; beſides, ſomewhat equivolent, or better for you, then that which you requeſted, may be given, and you not diſcern it, for the vehement intention of your eies upon your own will; or, the ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y thing may be granted, though not for the time, manner, means and meaſure, by you, to your ſelves propounded and from God expected. 3. I grant, the Lord may juſtly and mercifully for your good, either deny or croſſe you: And that for theſe Reaſons, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe of the indiſpoſition of your heart to receive
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:121309:66"/> ſuch a bleſſing, or ſo much. <hi>Paul</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thrice, and had this anſwer in the end, <hi>My Grace is ſufficient for thee,</hi> to uphold and give thee <hi>victory,</hi> better then thy deſired freedome. Time may come when you will kneel down and adore the wiſdome and ſeaſonableneſſe of ſuch croſſes. <hi>Poſſidonius</hi> in the life of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> gives a memorable example: the good <hi>Father</hi> being to viſit and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the people of a certain place, and having a guide to direct him, did not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding miſſe the way, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly fell into a by-path, by which means he eſcaped the bloody hands of ſome cruel <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> who lay in wait for him, to take away his life. I have read another paſſage of a godly man, that as he was going to take ſhipping for <hi>France,</hi> he brake his leg, and it pleaſed Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſo to order it, that the ſhip whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſhould have gone was that time caſt away, and not a man ſaved; thus may God lead you beſides your expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and intentions, to preſerve you from ſome danger, which otherwiſe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in wait for you. The ſick patient is never better ſerved, then when he is denied, and God denieth our will ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:121309:66"/> that we may have our will. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> It may be to quicken your zeal, which delay and denial doth enflame. Our zeal if it be true is like lime, which groweth hotter by how much more water is caſt upon it. Before you were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate in your deſire and requeſts: and God likes not that temper: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore he delaies. Let the infant faſt, it will know the dug the better, and ſeek it the faſter. Stop the Lure and the Flawk will mend her pitch, and fly the higher; and if God deny or delay faithful prayers, it is to encreaſe them, to exerciſe his gifts, your graces, that ſo you may ſearch and trie your waies more throughly, be more ready to open your ears to the cries of the poor, and for ever after more love and prize the favour of God. 4. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, pray ſtill, caſt not away your <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor,</hi> pray for bleſſings abſolutely promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, although you could never be aſſured of having your particular requeſt; grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; wait upon God, and eye the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; hold out faith and patience; reſt aſſured, <hi>holy deſires</hi> can never finally be loſt; the longer he holdeth ſouls in u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, it argues God will give more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly. Great engines move ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:121309:67"/> ſmall things are quickly wheeled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. Great ſhips that go long Voya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, before they come home are uſually richly laden; an Oak is long growing, but proves a great tree and long-lived, whereas a Gourd which grows up in a night, in another is ſmitten with a worm and dieth; a bleſſing that is long a coming, is ordinarily a great one when it doth come. God intendeth not your hinderance, no, no; go on, bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, make up a good and great trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt another day. In the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints (O bleſſed Society!) there is a ſtock of Prayers continually going on and growing. He is a rich man indeed, that is rich in Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Caſe </seg>5</label> What ſhould a man ſettle his minde upon, while he is framing and directing his Prayer?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 1. Take heed of fancying any form or ſhape, as the object to terminate your thoughts. Give not the <hi>active intellect</hi> too much liberty, to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie into things not yet reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led; or to preſent and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them in another notion then reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed. <hi>Sorutator Majeſtatis opprime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur à gloria.</hi> Your eyes will be dazeled by looking on this Sun. To frame
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:121309:67"/> the <hi>Divine Nature</hi> in any imaginary likeneſſe is bold Idolatrie: it is to ſeek that, which in that vaſt Oce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite <hi>Being</hi> cannot be found, but in mans imagination, preſenting wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is not, and ſo making an Idol. 2. Begin <hi>with,</hi> and aſcend <hi>by</hi> the now glorious <hi>Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of Chriſt, towards the <hi>Deity,</hi> let that ſerve you inſtead of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder. 3. Be well acquainted <hi>with,</hi> and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally mindeful <hi>of</hi> the <hi>Divine</hi> Attributes, wherein the Lord hath deſcribed himſelf to <hi>Abraham, Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets. Majeſty, power, bounty and love do ſhine in the Attributes of God, and we may make uſe of them eſpecially that are fitteſt to raiſe the heart in deſire and faith, or to ſtrike it with awe and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as occaſion requireth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. When you have done that you can, by reading and meditating: conceive an excellency of glory, not to be fadom'd by humane reaſon; and ſo quiet the minde till you be qualified for the beatifical Viſion. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Caſe </seg>6</label>
            </p>
            <p>But when I do ſo, my-thinks my own unworthineſſe doth ſo much the more preſent it ſelf, and makes me ready to ſink through fear?</p>
            <p>True it is, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Oppoſita juxta ſe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſita ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:121309:68"/> eluceſcunt:</hi> Contraries do illuſtrate one another; the glorious day diſcovers the blackneſſe of the night: the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Muſick rendreth jarring ſounds more unacceptable: and the neerer we draw neer into Gods preſence, the better we ſee him in the Word, ſo much more doth our vileneſſe appear, <hi>Job</hi> 42.5, 6. But be ye well aſſured, 1. That this doth not encreaſe your unworthineſſe (no more then the light of the Sun en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth deformity,) but onely unvail it ſo much the more; the Looking-Glaſſe doth not augment the ſpots in the face, but diſcovers them to the eye, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, they may be loathed and waſhed off, ſo it is here. 2. The more unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy you are in your own eyes, by that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion: the more worthy are you in the account of God, who judgeth not as man judgeth. 3. Your worthineſſe for which you are accepted by God, is not in your ſelves, but in Chriſt, <hi>the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of the Saints.</hi> Keep your eye upon <hi>him,</hi> who is a cloud, a skreen, or ſhelter for poor guilty man, againſt thoſe pure and piercing beams; So that God <hi>ſeeth not iniquity in Jacob.</hi> 4. Know and conſider, that <hi>Prayer</hi> is not onely a
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:121309:68"/> 
               <hi>duty,</hi> but a <hi>means</hi> to procure worthineſſe and acceptance. <hi>Ask of me and I will give,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ask and yee ſhall receive.</hi> Ask that your <hi>joy may be full.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as they might boldly come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto the inner Court of the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> to whom he held forth the golden Scepter: So may we confidently ſpeak to God; his commands, and ſweet promiſes, his bountiful invitations, and aimable titles, with the effectual Interceſſion of Chriſt, muſt be oppoſed to the ſenſe of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe.</p>
            <p>And ſo from <hi>Caſes</hi> we proceed to <hi>Conditions</hi> required, that your prayers may be acceptable, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Perſon</hi> muſt be rightly qualified, and all the <hi>graces</hi> muſt be ſet on work, as about a matter of greateſt importance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Perſon</hi> muſt be rightly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified: and that as ſtanding in a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold relation: 1. To God. 2. To men. 3. To himſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To God, he muſt <hi>acknowledge</hi> God, and be acknowledged of God, by vertue of the Covenant, and of the Mediatour, intitling Petitioners to the promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>He that cometh to God muſt believe that he is, and</hi> that he
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:121309:69"/> 
               <hi>is the rewarder of thoſe that diligently ſeek him;</hi> this you muſt be well ſettled in, that he is ſuch in himſelf, and ſuch to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you as he ſtands deſcribed in his Word; and be <hi>acknowledged</hi> of God: or elſe the anſwer will be, <hi>I have no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in you, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I accept an offering at your hands, Malac.</hi> 1.10. I care not for your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, I reſpect not your performances.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To men, whether friends or ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to be in love and charity, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.23, 24. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.14, 15. Gods boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to us requires our obedience to him, he will not <hi>give,</hi> except we <hi>forgive: if you forgive men their treſpaſſes, your heavenly Father will alſo forgive you.</hi> Though our love to men be not a <hi>cauſe</hi> of our acceptance with God, yet it is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary <hi>antecedent;</hi> yea, foraſmuch as he hath made us this promiſe here, our <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving</hi> others ſeemeth to have the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of an <hi>intervenient cauſe,</hi> a cauſe <hi>ſine qua non,</hi> of his forgiving us. How can we look our Father in the face, or ask him a bleſſing, when we are conſcious that he knows, hatred or heart-burning between us and our brethren.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Towards himſelf; he muſt be an
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:121309:69"/> 
               <hi>hater of ſin</hi> (if I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear my prayer) ſo as to purſue it with a ſerious intent and hearty deſire to have it taken and killed; he muſt be a <hi>lover</hi> of <hi>Gods image</hi> where ever it truly appears; it was the expreſſion of a <hi>good</hi> man, <hi>I dare not but love him, in whom I ſee any thing of Chriſt. If thou love not thy brother whom thou haſt ſeen, how canſt thou l ve God, whom thou haſt not ſeen?</hi> As <hi>Dalilah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Sampſon,</hi> ſo it may be ſaid to moſt men, <hi>how can yee ſay,</hi> yee love God or good men, ſeeing your heart is not with them. Now that you may not be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, take along with you ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of men and women thus qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They will be ready to part with any thing for Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.46. to ſell all and purchaſe this <hi>pearl. Phil.</hi> 3.8. <hi>I count all things but dung,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now I know that thou loveſt me,</hi> ſaith the Lord to <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſeeing thou art content to part with thy <hi>onely</hi> ſon at my word! Chriſt hath taken up <hi>their</hi> ſouls unto the top of <hi>Piſgah,</hi> and diſcovered to them the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and hath given them ſuch more then ordinary taſtes of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:121309:70"/> the world to come, that the whole low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er world, though vailed with the moſt glorious and gliſtring temptations, is all ſcorned as too low a bribe to draw off the ſoul from <hi>Chriſt. Theodoſius</hi> will value his Chriſtianity above his Empire. <hi>Luther</hi> would rather be <hi>Chriſtianus ruſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, quàm Ethnicus Alexander,</hi> (i. e.) a Chriſtian clown then an Heathen Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. <hi>Secondly,</hi> They are not long angry, but eaſily entreated in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God, or in their tranſactions with men, ready to any good office: Like the waters at the foot of Sion, that run ſoftly: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Charity ſuffereth long and is kinde; Charity envieth not, it doth not behave it ſelf unſeemly.</hi> James 3.17. <hi>The wiſdome that is from above, is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle and eaſie to be entreated, full of mercy and good works.</hi> A good garment for a Chriſtian, without which he is naked before God. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They are open-ear'd and handed towards any in miſery. They reſent the miſery of others, their hearts do yearn over the <hi>Brethrens</hi> calamities. As <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter, when ſhe ſaw the childe in the Ark of Bull-ruſhes, (a very ſad Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle!) and that the babe wept, the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:121309:70"/> Text ſaies, <hi>She had compaſſion on him, Exod.</hi> 2.6. And ſo in the good <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan,</hi> when he paſſed by the poor man who had fallen among thieves, and ſaw him ſtripped of all, wounde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; this good man had an eye and an hand toward him: So it is in this caſe. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urthly,</hi> They are wondrous cheerful, in ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing heavy conditions: eſpecially in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the <hi>truth</hi>'s ſake, rejoycing in the hope of the glory of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. Which hope holds them above fears; ſo that they are not moved with love or fear, (as the <hi>Romans</hi> wrote on their Targets) though at firſt they may be daunted, yet at length they look up and gather ſtrength. <hi>Hannah</hi> was much troubled for want of a childe, ſhe went to God by fervent prayer, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was no more ſad. With thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>David</hi> was wont to cheer himſelf in the depth of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, <hi>the Lord hath heard my prayer! Fifthly,</hi> They can deny <hi>themſelves</hi> whom God cannot deny, in their fervent ſuits, being divorced from their own will by an over-powering work of <hi>the Spirit</hi> in Legal convictions; they le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not to their own underſtandings. Thus muſt the perſon be qualified fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prayer.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:121309:71"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Then it ſeems a wicked, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous <hi>perſon</hi> may not pray? Or if he may, his prayer will be to little or no purpoſe, ineffectual?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Prayer is conſiderable two waies, 1. In a large ſenſe, as a commanded du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and part of Gods worſhip, in its or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary uſe, whereby we give God the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his <hi>Omniſciency, Mercy, Power,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdome.</hi> 2. In a more ſtrict ſenſe, for the putting up of a formal requeſt or petition to God, which may conſiſt in an exerciſe of the ſoul, and of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in it, whether common or ſaving. And the Anſwer to the Objection I ſhall lay thus before you. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Prayer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as a duty muſt be performed by unrighteous men: and a great ſin it is to neglect it; it is the worſt thing can be ſaid of any man, that he reſtraineth prayer before God; in <hi>Job</hi> 15.4. it is joined with caſting away the fear of God, <hi>i. e.</hi> with profeſſed Atheiſme and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe. Mans defects as he now ſtands, can give no excuſe to a wilful neglect: his impotency cannot preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice Gods authority, or diminiſh his own duty. Prayer is a thing good in it ſelf, and not evil <hi>propter fieri,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:121309:71"/> it is done, but by accident, <hi>vitio perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae,</hi> by reaſon of ſome defects cleaving unto it; In which ſenſe only it is, that the Scriptures cry down the prayers of wicked men, as an <hi>abomintion,</hi> as <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.8. &amp; 28.9.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> on the Text gives that ſame gloſſe.</note> not that it is ſo as to the ſubſtance of the duty, but becauſe, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be they pray for, they reſolve to go on in their wicked practiſes, as the latter Scripture expreſſes in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of it, <hi>He that turneth his ear from hearing the Law, even his prayer ſhall be abomination.</hi> And beſides, though pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, not made <hi>in faith,</hi> cannot <hi>pleaſe God,</hi> as the prayers of holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en do; yet being good for the ſubſtance of it, giving glory to God of ſundry Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of his, it may <hi>probably</hi> avail for procurement of a temporal bleſſing: as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> prayers had the reward of mens praiſes. <hi>Ahabs</hi> humiliation, and the <hi>Ninevites</hi> repentance procured a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay of puniſhment. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Prayer conſidered as a formal requeſt in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the ſoul, and of ſome common graces in it, eſpecially argumentative prayer, may <hi>perhaps</hi> avail through the help of Gods Spirit, bringing the ſoul into a better temper and frame, and ſo
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:121309:72"/> making it capable of ſpiritual <hi>and</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſings. Prophane <hi>Eſau</hi> could go to his father for a childes portion, and ſo could the Prodigal, and had it.</p>
            <p>I come to the <hi>ſecond</hi> qualification of acceptable <hi>effectual prayer, viz.</hi> all the <hi>Graces</hi> muſt be ſet on work: <hi>faith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, humility,</hi> the very lungs whence prayer is bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Faith,</hi> (for where it lives, it will breath in devotion) in the <hi>Divine</hi> Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, touching what is there revealed, to be true, becauſe he hath ſaid it. Faith, in Gods Providence, concerning his wiſe and <hi>ſtable</hi> government of the world: that he can and will provide for bodies and ſouls, out of the rich Magazine of infinite tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſures laid up in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> If an <hi>Elijah</hi> want, the Ravens will come at Gods command, and bring him mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> morning and evening: Faith, in Gods promiſes, (which are the air and elements wherein faith breaths) touching free ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, ſanctification and acceptation of you unto life and glory for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake. <hi>If any want wiſdome, let him ask</hi> of God, who giveth liberally unto all men, but let him ask in <hi>Faith,</hi> nothing wavering, <hi>James</hi> 1.5, 6. And again, the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:121309:72"/> Apoſtle willeth men to pray—with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubting, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8. (the more doubting the leſſe faith.) For he that cometh unto God muſt believe, &amp;c. as before. He that wants this ingredient, doth no more then <hi>deny</hi> his own requeſts, and ſhuts up the door of Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How may a man know when he praies in faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. By an hearty reſiſtance, with ſome comfortable power and gaining ſtrength, againſt fears, doubts and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions that do oppoſe. <hi>This is the victory that overcometh the world, even your faith,</hi> it overcomes a world of enemies, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.4. It is a victorious grace, and it acts by purifying the heart, and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying luſts. And though a man may be foiled now and then in a skirmiſh, when very hotly charged, and over-born by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, yet theſe foils tend to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> further eſtabliſhment, and like the tree, ſtands the firmer for ſhaking. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a fruit of praying in faith. 2. By ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>adineſſe of the heart, at leaſt in <hi>deſire</hi> and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, upon the right object God in Chriſt. <hi>Moſes</hi> his hand being under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propt and ſtayed by <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> (as by the <hi>Spirit</hi> and faith) were ſteady un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:121309:73"/> the going down of the Sun, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.12. Chriſt continued all night in prayer to God, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.12. But take heed of the error of the <hi>Heathen, Matth.</hi> 6.7. that thought to be heard for their much ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; and of the hypocriſie of the Scribes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.14. who made long prayers for the <hi>praiſe of men.</hi> Carry an equal minde in the duty; they are not gifts, but graces that God looks for in prayer, 3. By that calmneſſe of minde after, truſting God with the ſucceſſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving patiently to wait. When <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.18. had made her ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God for a childe, it is ſaid, <hi>She went her way and did eat, and her counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was no more ſad.</hi> Which alteration hapned through an inward comfort of <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> which ſealed in her heart, that her prayers were heard. This is an effect of the witneſſing of the Spirit together with ours, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. A re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of the heart after duty, with a ſecret content, with an hidden approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If our hearts condemn us not, then we have confidence towards God, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.21. 4. By due care in the uſe of appointed means, not to cleave to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular means, with a ſinful reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:121309:73"/> to have mercy that way, or not at all. This is to limit a moſt free agent, to circumſcribe Gods will, and to ſtreigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our ſelves in a narrow path, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.41. 5. By conſtancy, even when the Lord ſeems to frown, and turn away his face. A notable inſtance you have in the woman of <hi>Canaan, Matth.</hi> 15.22. ſhe cried earneſtly after Chriſt, <hi>Have mercy on me, O Lord,</hi> &amp;c. One Copy hath it, <hi>and cried behinde him,</hi> which implies that Chriſt had turned his back on her, ſeeing her now coming towards him; well, the Diſciples intercede, he tells them, <hi>He was not ſent but to the lost ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi> She comes again, but receives a rough anſwer, <hi>It is not meet to take childrens bread and caſt it to dogs;</hi> out of all we may conclude, great faith to act that poor woman. View her temptations in that doubtful caſe (it is Mr. <hi>Boltons</hi> Obſervation in his Treatiſe <hi>Of the Nature and Roialties of ſaith.) Firſt,</hi> There was <hi>tentatio taciturnitatis,</hi> the trial of ſilence, ſhe prayes, and not a word comes. <hi>Secondly, Tentatio parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularitatis,</hi> firſt nothing, and then worſe then nothing, <hi>I am not ſent, but,</hi> &amp;c. as if he had ſaid, thou doſt not belong to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:121309:74"/> the election of grace: thou art not in Covenant; I came onely to my own, not to thee, therefore I will not help thee. <hi>Thirdly, Tentatio indignitatis;</hi> the trial of indignity, <hi>It is not meet,</hi> &amp;c. And yet ſee the ſtrength of her faith, <hi>Truth, Lord, yet the dogs eat of the crumbs:</hi> if ſhe may not have a childes, yet a dogs portion, if not childrens morſels, yet childrens crumbs, but ſuch as fall from the table, ſuch as they have no need of. She was that well reſolved Chriſtian, whoſe part is (as <hi>Luther</hi> ſometime ſaid) to believe things invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to hope for things deferr'd, and to love God when he ſeems moſt angry with, and oppoſite to him. With this meaſure of faith <hi>Chriſt</hi> is overcome: Oh, woman, great is thy faith! Such force there is in faithful-fervent prayer.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Second</hi> Grace to be ſet on work in prayer is <hi>Repentance. Waſh ye make ye clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes, ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then come and let us reaſon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 1.16, 17, 18. I will waſh mine hands in innocency, and ſo will I compaſſe <hi>thine Altar, O Lord,</hi> was <hi>Davids</hi> practice. Typified in <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:121309:74"/> waſhing of his feet, befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e he went into Sacrifice: and continued as a bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed rite among the <hi>Turks,</hi> to waſh and put off their ſhoes before they enter on their idol-worſhip. A plain doctrine that Saint <hi>James</hi> teacheth, <hi>ch.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 8. Draw nigh to God, &amp;c. cleanſe your hands ye ſinners, &amp;c. And the reaſon is, becauſe in prayer, you crave pardon of ſin and removal of judgements, with the favour of Gods bleſſed preſence, which cannot be without repentance. Conſcience of ſin unrepented of will clip and dull the wings of prayer, ſet a damp on the petitioner, ſeparate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and God; but the blood of Chriſt will cleanſe, cheer and elevate the ſoul, as the waters did <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hs</hi> Ark, far above all danger. Repentance is a Rain-bow, which if God ſee ſhining in our hearts, when we come before him, he will not <hi>drown</hi> the ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How may true penitency in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious hearts, be diſcerned from ſeigned ſorrow in graceleſſe perſons, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſin, and after ſay they repent, yet ſin again?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. A truly gracious ſoul, though it ſin, yet it makes no league o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> peace with ſin, but keeps the war on foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtill.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:121309:75"/> As <hi>Hannibal</hi> took an Oath to his father to maintain perpetual hoſtility with <hi>Rome:</hi> So have gracious ſouls covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od, to wage a perpetual war with ſin; though it ſometime receives a foil and loſſe, yet thereby it is more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged againſt the adverſary. Carnal coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit perſons once foiled, ſeldome come on again: but the true penitent ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and fights moſt valiantly, doubles his guard after unwarineſſe, ſtrengthens the battle after a blow, laying on more ſtrongly, after ſin hath been too hard; as we ſee in <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scripture-examples. 2. True grace gets advantage by the ſtirring and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times prevailing power of ſin, which meer <hi>nature</hi> cannot do: <hi>it</hi> alwaies lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, the heart is made worſe, ſin loved, holineſſe loathed ſome degrees more, and ſecurity ſurpriſeth the ſoul. When as in gracious hearts, every thing falleth out otherwiſe; the heart is made bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſin more loathed, holineſſe prized ſome degrees more, &amp; the ſoul ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; like the Giant <hi>Anteus,</hi> who in his wreſtling with <hi>Hercules,</hi> is ſeigned to get ſtrength by every fall to the ground.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third</hi> Grace required to be acted
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:121309:75"/> in prayer is <hi>humility:</hi> which may ſerve as the pins of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, whereby the ſoul climbeth up to He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven. He that would leap higheſt muſt ſtoop low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. God exalteth the humble, whilſt he reſiſteth the proud and ſends them empty away. As men uſe to lay up the richeſt wine in the loweſt Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lars, ſo doth God the choiceſt mercies in humble and lowly hearts. <hi>Chriſt</hi> when he was upon the earth did moſt for thoſe that were <hi>humble,</hi> and ſo continues to do. The truly humble ſoul is Gods ſecond Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>I will dwell with the cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſpirit.</hi> The Valleys ſhall laugh with ſatneſſe, when the Hills are barren. And this Grace may be diſcerned thus;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> By a grateful diſpoſition for former favours. Of old, a pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce-offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was appointed to be joine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with the treſpaſſe-offering: to teach the Church ever to join praiſe with prayer. But the proud heart hath never enough, is ever unthankful. <hi>Secondly,</hi> By a mean and low conceit of your ſelves, and your own unworthineſſe before God. Like that of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 18.27. <hi>that am but duſt and aſhes:</hi> or of <hi>David,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o fooliſh was I, as a beaſt before thee: and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gur,</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:121309:76"/> Prov. 30.2. I am more brutiſh then any man; or as that <hi>Martyr,</hi> who cried out, <hi>Gehenna ſum Domine,</hi> &amp;c. Lord, thou art Heaven, but I am as bad as Hell. <hi>Tantillitas noſtra,</hi> ſaid <hi>Ignatius</hi> of himſelf and his Colleagues; the humble man like <hi>Paul,</hi> doth not elevate, but ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate his ſins againſt himſelf, vails all the top-ſails and ſits down in the duſt, <hi>Job</hi> 42.6. <hi>Mine eye ſeeth thee, therefore I abhorre my ſelf in duſt and aſhes;</hi> when he had a glorious apparition of God, he vaniſhed into nothing in his own thoughts. The ſtars vaniſh when the Sun appears: and our poor Candle va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth into a diſappearance, when the glory of God ariſeth in the thoughts of the humble. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By this, when heavenly Objects appear in our eye great and beautiful more and more. As in <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 4.6. who preferred Gods favour to all things; and in <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil. 3.8. who counted <hi>all things but dung,</hi> in compariſon of <hi>the excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt.</hi> He undervalues a whole sky full of ſtars, to one <hi>Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> And as holy <hi>Lambert,</hi> None but Chriſt, none but Chriſt. To them that believe he is precious, they can ſee
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:121309:76"/> thoſe beauties and excellencie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in him, that are not diſcovered to others. To unbelievers, heavenly objects are as ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent pearls in an heap of ſand, and a Mine of gold covered over with rubbiſh and earth. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> By meekneſſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to yield in all your own cauſes, but reſoluteneſſe in the cauſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, in behalf of his truth. <hi>Moſes,</hi> one of the meekeſt men on earth, yet who more hot and zealous in the ſervice of God? The three children, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16. are well reſolved in the like caſe, and will not ſuffer truth to fall for them. <hi>Luther</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards not himſelf nor the rich <hi>preſents,</hi> but is eaten up with the zeal of Gods houſe. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> By a patient waiting upon God, till the time appointed, <hi>He that believeth will not make haſt:</hi> to ſtep aſide through indirect means to obtain what is prayed for or promiſed, not <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, charms, witchcraft</hi> to finde things loſt, to obtain health or grow rich; who art thou that feareſt God and obeyeſt the voice of his ſervants, and yet walkeſt in darkneſſe, wait upon God and ſtay thy ſelf on the Lord. We re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of <hi>Zachary,</hi> that he prayed for a childe heretofore, while there was any ordinary ground of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:121309:77"/> hope, but after (as it is probable) left off <hi>that ſuit,</hi> but not waiting, what God would do for him, and he had his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt at laſt. Prayers are often granted, long before manifeſted. Thus muſt grace be exerciſed in acceptable prayer: it is the <hi>Palaeſtra,</hi> the <hi>Arena,</hi> the Artillary-yard of all our graces in which they muſt ſhew their activity. And thus much may ſuffice for the diſcovery of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions required in prayer.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place we come to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, not to the reading, or repeating, ſaying over of prayers onely, not to a cold, careleſſe performance of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at all; but to fervent praying: this is praying with power, whereof that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage is fitly verified, and rightly to be underſtood, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.11. <hi>Behold he prayeth. Saul</hi> ſtruck to the ground remained three days without ſight, and did neither eat nor drink: but, <hi>behold he prayeth,</hi> (i. e.) with all his might, as one that taketh no denial. To <hi>pray fervently,</hi> is the point in hand, firſt undertaken, and hitherto proſecured. And to this there are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all Motives: and they may be taken, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irſt,</hi> From the Lord, to whom we muſt pray. <hi>Secondly,</hi> From men. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom prayer it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:121309:77"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> From the Lord; and then you may take into conſideration, ſuch Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives as theſe: 1. He commands that you ſhould pray to him as you love him, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> ſtrongly, vehemently, and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. My ſon, give me thy hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. It is a ſpecial part of <hi>Divine</hi> worſhip, and if you make conſcience of any duty, you will of this eſpecially, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.2.2. He delights in earneſt and zealous prayers and petitioners, (God is not a man, who may be tired with unceſſant ſuits, and frequent viſits, (<hi>Prov.</hi> 25.17.) as was the unjuſt Judge, and the Diſciples with the poor womans cries, repeating the ſame requeſt over and over) Such were <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> highly commended of God, for their skill &amp; art in <hi>praying;</hi> one, the <hi>meekeſt man on earth,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other, a man <hi>after Gods own heart;</hi> and he can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them nothing; provided they referre the time, and meaſure to him. As men take delight in the deep-mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h'd hound, and the ſhrill ſound of the Trumpet, and the loud report of the Piec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; ſo doth God take delight in the <hi>fervent reports</hi> of his people. 3. He is ready to return an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſuch <hi>fervent</hi> prayers; hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ears are open to the cries of his people. The <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles</hi>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:121309:78"/> among the <hi>Romans,</hi> had ever the door ſtanding open to all that had occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for requeſts or complaints: Even ſo are the doors of Gods mercy open unto <hi>fervent</hi> ſuppliants. He is that friend ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in <hi>Luke</hi> 11. Ready to hear when any <hi>friend</hi> doth knock. God is not like that Idol <hi>Baal,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.27. Of whom <hi>Elijah</hi> ſaid to his Prieſts (when with much clamour they cried unto him, but had no anſwet) Cry aloud, for he is a God, either talking, or purſuing, or in a journey, or peradventure he ſleepeth; Or like the Heathen <hi>Jupiter,</hi> who when the <hi>Grecians</hi> and <hi>Trojans</hi> were by the ears, was gone to viſit his old friends, <hi>Oceanus</hi> and <hi>Tethis: The Lord</hi> is alwaies nigh at hand to all that call upon him fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently. It was never known that God ſaid to any ſuitor as <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> I have no lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; or go away, and come to morrow, if it were convenient and ſeaſonable for him to grant the requeſt at preſent. He is as ready to beſtow mercy, as a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers breaſt is to give milk, he waits but for drawing. It was the commendation of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his clemency and ſweet diſpoſition, that it was to him as if he
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:121309:78"/> received a benefit, if he might have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to forgive an injury; and ſuch is the excellent freeneſſe of <hi>Divine bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els,</hi> that the Lord <hi>waiteth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e gracious,</hi> and <hi>mercy pleaſeth him!</hi> 4. He hath made many ſweet and precious promiſes to ſuch as pray to him with ſupplication and thankſgiving, Pſal. 50.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. <hi>Call upon me, and I will hear. God will hear:</hi> But upon what terms? upon condition that you call, ſeek and knock, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7, 8. Open thy mouth wide, and I will fill it. Yea, <hi>Whatſoever ye ask the Father in my Name believing, he will do it</hi> for you. There is a promiſe for whatſoever you have need to pray for. Who then is ſo dull, that will not be quickned by thoſe allurements? ſo ſtubborn, as not to be won? ſo timorous, as not to be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by them? who will not ask, when his requeſt is ſo graciouſly accepted, ſo eaſily granted? 5. <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath taught you how to pray, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.9. He putteth words as it were to your mouths, and tels you what to ask. He died and roſe again, to make way for your p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſons and prayers into Gods preſence, calling you to come unto him with your petitions, and he will preſent them to the Father.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:121309:79"/> 6. The <hi>Divine Attributes</hi> ſhould move you, whether <hi>abſolute</hi> or <hi>relative: Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute,</hi> as his Omniſciency, Omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Mercy, Truth and Faithfulneſſe, his bounty and Glory, all magni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ied by petitioners, and excerciſed by granting requeſts. <hi>Relative,</hi> ſo he is called an hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, a Father, a gracious Lord; as it was ſaid of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> that he that dared to approach his preſence, ſeemed not to know his greatneſſe, and he that durſt not, ſeemed not to know his goodneſſe. All of God ſhould encourage the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Faith to come unto him, in all zealous humility and devout reverence. 7. The honour to be admitted his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and to have conference with him. Men account it a great honour to ſtand before a great <hi>Prince</hi> of the earth (who is but a man in a greater letter) and to conve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe with him. The Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> pronounced them happy men, happy ſervants, which could ſtand continually befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Solomon,</hi> and to hear his wiſdom, 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 10.8. The <hi>Perſian</hi> Kings made it a part of their great condeſcention, to manife<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t themſelves unto their Subjects: But what honour is this, to ſtand in the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence chamber of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:121309:79"/> that</hi> Glorious Lord of all the earth, to converſe and have fellowſhip with him? Conſider it is a favour given only to a few, even ſuch as the Lord ſhall call, and they are but few, compared with the numbers that ſit in darkneſſe, and call not upon the Name of the Lord. This ſhould move you to pray often, and ever in earneſt; he is eaſie to be entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and upbraideth not, the oftner we come, the more welcome, and the more we <hi>acquaint</hi> our ſelves wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h him, the more <hi>good</hi> cometh to us, <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 22.21. Our often addreſſes and requeſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o men, may ſoon receive a repulſe, but cannot weary <hi>infiniteneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second ſort of Motives may be taken from men, and ſo 1. From a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of your ſelves. 2. Of others. 1. Conſider your ſelves. <hi>Firſt,</hi> What danger and loſſe growes upon omiſſion of prayer, as 1. Your outward eſtate li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth open to the curſe of God, to be ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by all, or any of the Creatures. It is the preſence of God that muſt preſerve our outward eſtates, and make up a peace with us and the Creatures. <hi>Rebellis enim facta eſt quia homo numini, creatura homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</hi> The creatures rebell aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſt man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:121309:80"/> he rebelled againſt God: Now as Noble mens ſervants will <hi>draw</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their Lord, and as Souldiers fight for their General, ſo it is here, God is the Lord of Hoſts, and they continue to this day according to his Ordinance, for they are all ſervants ready preſt to ſeize a ſinner, and to do execution on him and his, as a Traitor and Rebell to higheſt Majeſty. Now it is Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence that can only aboliſh this enmity; And how ſhall we <hi>confine</hi> God amongſt us without <hi>fervent praying?</hi> Prayer is like the Golden chain with which the <hi>Tyrians</hi> (when <hi>Alexander</hi> beleagur'd them) bound faſt their tutelar God <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo,</hi> that he might not leave their City. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Your inward parts and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties run all out of order, like a wide wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe whereon comes neither Sun or dew; or as a Clock that no man looks unto, will ſoon be out of order, and at a ſtand, and as a ſore wound which is not dreſſed, or plyed with freſh ſalves, will corrupt and feſter; ſo it is with men that neglect or omit prayer. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is one of the worſt ſignes can be, that men are and continue ſtrangers to God, that they depend on themſelves, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:121309:80"/> like the ſwine, who eat the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>corns, but never look up to the tree that bare them. What dammage likewiſe comes upon a cold careleſſe performance of it? for ſo you miſpend precious time, lay your ſelves open to the enmity of the world, who take you to be zealous men indeed, and under that notion hate and trouble you, and all this without any recompenſe from God, becauſe you are not ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. And ſo often you pray, or rather repeat a prayer, in this cold formal manner, you take Gods Name in vain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider the benefit comes to the ſoul, and ſociety of Chriſtians, by <hi>fervent prayer,</hi> which can hardly be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined or uttered. For 1. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ever a bleſſed means to mitigate or remove judgments, what ſpiritual burdens the ſoul lieth under, by reaſon of ſin remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within, or enemies without. It was <hi>Davids Catholicon</hi> in all his troubles and trials: When you have none to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to, or eaſe you, think what an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe it is to have ſuch a boſom open. 2. A means it is richly to ſupply all your wants. <hi>Prayer,</hi> like the Heavens, hath influence on all things below it; as
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:121309:81"/> appears from the Prophetick Prayer of <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8. And the practiſe of <hi>David</hi> in the book of Pſalms, and of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gur, Prov.</hi> 30.8. It brings and keeps the heart in good temper, and fills it with Spiritual joy and ſweetneſſe, <hi>John</hi> 16.24. Ask and your joy ſhall be full: No ſorrow can ſtand before the God of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. <hi>Davids</hi> heart was more oft out of tune than his harp, he prayes, and then <hi>cries, Return to thy reſt O my ſoul.</hi> In many of the Pſalms, the beginnings are ſull of trouble, but by that time he hath prayed a while, the ends are full of joy and aſſurance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.22. &amp; 51. It faſtneth on us as with Spirituall buckles, all our Spiritual armour, and ſets God on work for us. It is a lock for the night, and a key for the day, to open Gods treaſury, and let in the beams of the <hi>Sun of righteouſneſſe</hi> upon us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider what need you have to pray to God <hi>fervently.</hi> If you know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly weighed, what a great work you have to do, in a ſhort time, and in what danger you are, upon the brink of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and Satan goes about ſeeking to devour you, ſay then, have you not cauſe in reſpect of your ſelves to work in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:121309:81"/>2. Motives may be taken from conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of others, whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nemies or friends. Enemies you have many, to your perſons, profeſſion and practice in cloſe following the Captain of your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Pſal. 3.1. Many there are that riſe up againſt me. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.12. <hi>O our God, wilt thou not judge them, we have no might againſt this great compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that cometh againſt us, neither know we what to do, but our eies are upon thee.</hi> Your friends are ſick in body, or troubled in minde, with fears, doubts, deſertions, and ſuggeſtions, carnal or Satanical; as <hi>Paul</hi> was, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. Perſecuted and impriſoned as <hi>Peter</hi> was, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.5. or lying under heavy rods, one way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; perhaps imployed about weighty matters by ſea or land, tending eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to unthrone Satan, to root out Anti-Chriſt, and to enlarge the Kingdom of Chriſt: Such moving objects you have enough at home, and you may hear of more abroad! The great dangers we are ſenſibly in, by reaſon of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>enemies,</hi> ſhould move and awaken us to improve all our intereſt in Chriſt, to ſave us, <hi>or elſe we periſh,</hi> and ſo be made the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful'ſt ſpectacle that was ever yet beheld.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:121309:82"/> 
               <hi>A fruitfull land makes he barren for the ſins of the people that dwel therein.</hi> May not we tremble to think what will befall us? To cloſe this, Can you ſee God diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd, Satan advantaged, to domineer, a flouriſhing Church endangered, a dear Country like a mother bleeding to death, a brother, nay, many brethren oppreſſed, diſtreſſed, and yet be ſilent? Can you hear of what is preached on houſe-tops, without ſighing? Can you look on the dolefull face of things with dry eyes? O hard-hearted! <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſome great work in hand: a great and effectual door is opened, and there are many adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and will you not ſo much as pray to God for help? They are curſed with a bitter curſe which come not in to help the Lord againſt the mighty.</p>
            <p>A third and laſt ſort of Motives are taken from Prayer it ſelf; ſuch kind of praying, <hi>Firſt,</hi> It diſtinguiſheth between the gracious and the graceleſſe ſoul; it declares the ſacrifice to be more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. <hi>Cain</hi> offered a ſacrifice as well as <hi>Abel,</hi> but <hi>ſaith</hi> put the difference. As <hi>faith</hi> puts a difference, between the works of Heathens and the works of Chriſtians, though not for the matter,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:121309:82"/> yet for the manner; ſo do faithfull fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayers, between the ſound and the rotten Chriſtian. It puts a difference betwixt the <hi>Abba-fathers</hi> of a child, and the <hi>Ave-Maries</hi> of a ſuperſtitious Papiſt; betwixt the devotion of a Saint, and the devotion of a ſinner; the crie: of a Saint, and the howlings of an hypocrite; theſe make a great and long noiſe, the other only ſend up ſtrong cries, as well, and more in private then in publique. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is ever effectual, and hath been moſt ſucceſsfull. <hi>Vitus The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dorus</hi> ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>king of the prayers <hi>Luther</hi> made in reference to a Diet at <hi>Ausburg,</hi> wherein matters were like to go againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, wrote thus, <hi>Non dubito quin illius preces, magnum momentum ad deſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratam hanc cauſam comitiorum ſint allatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae;</hi> he doubted not but <hi>Luthers</hi> prayers would go near to turn the ſtream. No man ever thus ſought help of God in vain. Witneſſe <hi>Abraham, Moſes, Joſhuah, Elijah, a man ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect to like paſſions with us; Hannah, Daniel,</hi> with thouſands more, who were ſent away as <hi>Ruth</hi> from <hi>Boaz,</hi> with their boſom full of bleſſings; as <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> from <hi>David,</hi> with a royall revenue; as <hi>Achſah, Calebs</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:121309:83"/> from her father, with upper and nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſprings: or as <hi>Moſes</hi> from the mount, with their faces ſhining. A Chriſtian cannot want ſupplies, ſo long as he can pray for them; as they were wont to ſay of the <hi>Pope,</hi> he could never want money, ſo long as he could hold a pen in his hand to write for it. When the man can find a fervent-praying heart, God will find a pitying heart and a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying hand. The Ark and the Mercy-ſeat, were never, nor ever ſhall be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſuch as you inſtance for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of prayer, were all extraordinary, eminent men, good and holy, while I am mean, poor, vile, and cannot hope to prevail as they?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. I would know, who they are that have moſt need of mercy, and are ſo preſt to uſe ſtrength and fervency with God, as penitent ſinners, throughout the whole book of God. <hi>Paenitens loco juſti, apud Deum;</hi> a penitent ſinner is juſt in Gods account. As <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican, Mary Magdalen,</hi> the thief on the Croſs, ſinners in grain, yet humbled and accepted. As for <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the like, they were holy men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:121309:83"/> as there are many in the world now, though not ſo eminent, yet as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, and as powerfull in praying as they were. 2. I ſay, that the ſucceſſe and effectualneſſe of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayer, is not ſo much from the faith and fervency of the Petitioner, as from the mercy of God, and merit of Chriſt: Cry and <hi>pray fervently</hi> unto God, and reſt on the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But I am ſtreightned and want time to pray morning and evening, as you direct?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Have you time for other buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to eat, drink, ſleep, labour, and take your pleaſure, and none to pray? Have you time to <hi>game</hi> and drink, to buy and ſell, and none to pray? This is the part of a worldling, of <hi>the man</hi> of this life. 2. Wiſely improve your time, and beware of contracting upon your ſelves that burden of oppreſſing varieties, which keep men down, and imploy them in ſuch an exceſſe of matters in the earth, as with that <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Alva,</hi> they have no time to mind or look up to heaven. 3. Redeem at one time, what is inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably loſt at another; You may be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the word of truth and experience,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:121309:84"/> there is no hinderance of work nor loſſe of time in continuing this exerciſe. Gods bleſſing doth more then recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſuch expences. <hi>A whet is no let.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That righteous men are very prevalent in prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While mens hands <hi>are full of blood,</hi> the Lord will not he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.15. <hi>If I regard iniquity in my heart,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. Impenitent perſons, ſuch I mean as are ſo in act or diſpoſition, either they pray not at all: they that have done evil hate the light, leſt their deeds ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.20. The guilt of ſin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounding and reſting on them, doth diſcourage ſuch from prayer, and makes them willing to grow ſtrangers to God; as a treſpaſſer of his neighbour uſeth to ſay, I have done ſo or ſo againſt you, and am aſhamed to look you in the face: Or elſe, they pray in a cold f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>int manner, for form, rather then out of love; and ſuch prayers aſcend not. Now for the penitent righteous perſons, they are fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in prayer, wreſtling, with <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſtriving with <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting with <hi>Chriſt.</hi> As the tribes, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.27. are
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:121309:84"/> ſaid to ſerve God <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a ſtretching forth themſelves with all their might. And their prayers are worth ſomething: Witneſſe the prayers of <hi>Moſes, Joſhuah, Elijah, Davi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Daniel, Paul,</hi> no ſuch extraordinary preſidents but that a true penitent, skilled in prayer, and cloſing with the promiſes, may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail as much with God now, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they did then. Coldneſſe and infidelity are the main cauſes of ſo much fruitleſſe praying: and want of skill to obſerve returns, when they are fruitfull, doth occaſion unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and uncheerfulneſſe in good men.</p>
            <p>For a further illuſtration of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, it will do well to enqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Wherein are the prayers of the righteous ſo prevalent? <hi>Secondly,</hi> Why<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Wherein are they ſo effectual? <hi>A.</hi> The anſwer may be thus. They are effectual both to remove judgements and procure mercies. The work of prayer in the former will diſcover the later. It is effectual to remove judgements, and conſequently to bring mercies. <hi>Amos</hi> 7.1. to the 7. It removed the judgements of the graſhoppers and the fire: as <hi>Jonah</hi> prayed and removed a double death that
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:121309:85"/> had ſeized on him. It is the beſt Lever at a dead lift. It looſed the iron chains, and opened the iron gates; unlocked the windows of heaven. <hi>Eſt clavis inſtar quâ Dei penetralia aperiuntur. Jamblicus.</hi> Inſtead of a key wherewith Gods Cabinet is opened. The Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> knew this full well, and therefore ſets to work in good earneſt: as when a Cart is in a quagmire, if the horſes feel it coming, they'l pull the harder, till they have it out: ſo he. Prayer overcomes enemies; <hi>Achitophel</hi> withers before the prayer of <hi>David.</hi> The huge Army of a <hi>thouſand</hi> thouſand <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> ran away like cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards before the prayer of <hi>Aſa. Luther</hi> having prayed earneſtly to God in his chamber for the Churches ſucceſſe, came down ſaying, <hi>We have overcome, we have overcome!</hi> And ſo accordingly it proved. <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> being in the field with his Army, and in a great ſtreight for wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, commanded his <hi>Chriſtian</hi> band to pray unto their God in that diſtreſſe; they preſently fall down where they ſtood, and behold a plentifull ſhower followed immediatly, with thunder and lightning upon the enemy; called by him therefore from that time, <hi>Legio fulminatrix,</hi> the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:121309:85"/> lightning Legion. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> would have his Effigies made kneeling, (whenas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Emperours had theirs ſtanding, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing) to ſhew that he got all his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories by prayer. <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. reports of him, that he never took any war in hand, but firſt preſented his ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayers to God; <hi>Statis temporibus quotidiè ſolus cum ſolo D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o loquebatur. Fox</hi> in Martyr. relateth that the victory againſt <hi>Cedwell</hi> and <hi>Penda</hi> in the time of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> was aſcribed to the prayers of <hi>Oſwald;</hi> and the like of <hi>Allured</hi> againſt the <hi>Danes.</hi> What was ſaid of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.5. <hi>Their tongue is a ſharp ſword, ſwords are in their lips,</hi> may be truly ſaid of the tongues and lips of Gods people in prayer, they are as two-edged ſwords in their hands, to execute vengeance. Of all weapons, <hi>there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one like to this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, prayer is effectual to heal the ſick, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.14. <hi>If my people which are called by my Name, ſhall humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and pray, and ſeek my face,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then I will hear from Heaven, forgive their ſins, and heal the land.</hi> Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.17. We find that <hi>Abraham</hi> prayed, and <hi>the Lord healed Abimelech.</hi> Jam. 5.15. <hi>The prayer
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:121309:86"/> of Faith ſhall heal the ſick, and if they have committed ſins, they ſhall be forgiven them.</hi> And ſo ſhall be healed on both ſides. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing will not do it, prayer will not do it, but the <hi>prayer of faith</hi> ſhall. The ſtory of <hi>Luther</hi> is well known, how by his pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yers he recovered <hi>Theodorus Vitus</hi> of a conſumption, after the Phyſitians had given him up for dead. Such ſtrong breathings, like ſtrong winds, whilſt they are up keep great ſhowers from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and can blow away the blackeſt cloud; yea, blow the moſt ſmarting wounds whole. Such ſweet lips are ever dropping balm into the wounds of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. You ſee <hi>the prayers of the righteous</hi> are effectual to procure bleſſings, for the well-being of the common body. It is this that raiſes ſtorms to drive away ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and proſperous gales to bring mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and relief. It was the prayer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> that ſcatte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed the <hi>Spaniſh Armado</hi> like a miſt. I have read of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> who being once dangerouſly beſet with enemies, turned himſelf to God by prayers, faſting, and tears, the Lord was entreated to raiſe a tempeſt in the face of the enemy, to their diſcomfiture, and to turn <hi>Arbiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> one of their C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ptains to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:121309:86"/> his ſide, as <hi>Socrates</hi> relates it. Herein are the prayers of the righteous effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Why are their prayers ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual?</p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe all <hi>righteous</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are in houſe and Covenant with God; and therefore powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fully-effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: They are neer to him, dearer than Heaven and Earth. Now a domeſtick Attendant can ever prevail more with the Lord, than a retainer only. Their prayers go up as pillars of Incenſe, and come before the Lord, as the ſound of <hi>many waters. Sozomen</hi> reports of <hi>Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> that he never asked any thing of God, but obtained it. <hi>Hic homo potuit apud Deum quod voluit,</hi> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orded of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> he could have what he would of God. What <hi>Zedekiah</hi> ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to his Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers hypocri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ically, God ſaith to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſeriouſly, <hi>The King c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> deny you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> The Courtier that is a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vourite, gets more of his P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince many times with one requeſt, than an hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bandman or tradeſman can attain unto by twenty years labour. So doth the righteous man obt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in at the hands of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, having the <hi>Royalty</hi> of his e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r. Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:121309:87"/> rapture of <hi>Luther,</hi> in a certain prayer of his, <hi>fiat voluntas mea Domine!</hi> Lord let my will be done! And hence that requeſt of <hi>Bernard</hi> to his friend, whom he had adviſed for ſtrict and holy walking, <hi>&amp; cum talis fueris, memento mei. i. e.</hi> When thou art ſuch a one, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member me in thy prayers. All Gods family-ſervants are <hi>Iſraels,</hi> prevailers with him. <hi>Secondly,</hi> They have the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of prayer,</hi> whereby they are enabled to cry powerfully, <hi>Abba, Father.</hi> As the <hi>Spirit</hi> wrought powerfully in thoſe men, who were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, moved by the holy Ghoſt to ſpeak the Word of God to men, ſo it works power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in all <hi>righteous</hi> men ſpeaking to God. The <hi>Spirit</hi> doth both <hi>diſponere</hi> and <hi>excita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> give the habit and the act alſo, brings the fuel of good deſires into the ſoul, and there ſets it a burning; ſo that in a ſenſe they are the prayers of Chriſt indited by the Spirit, put up in his Name, and preſented by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his mediation. And it cannot otherwiſe be, but that they ſhould find the way back again, and reach that boſom whence they came. Theſe waters will riſe as high as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, eſpecially being conveyed by ſuch
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:121309:87"/> a Conduit-pipe. If the <hi>holy Spirit</hi> be the Inditer, the <hi>Son</hi> the Advocate, &amp; the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> the Regiſter of the Saints prayers, whatever weakneſſes there be, if not wilful, they cannot non-ſuit them in that Court. He cannot diſlike the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which himſelf hath framed: Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is the counterpane and reflection of his own good pleaſure, and he can no more reſiſt it, than his own will. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> They have diſpoſed and enlarged hearts, though not alwaies alike. <hi>Uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam eodem ardore orare poſſim!</hi> ſaith <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The more they pray, the better it is with them in that regard: The Lord doth enlarge their hearts, that they may pray, and then by prayer, that enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is encreaſed, that they may be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to receive more bleſſings. Prayer doth not merit mercy, but ſits us for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: empties the heart of <hi>ſelf,</hi> and takes in the more of God. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> There is nothing that can totally and finally hinder them: whilſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Heavens Favourite and Maſter of requeſts is their friend, and husband: whilſt the bleſſed <hi>Spirit</hi> is their aſſiſtant, and no ſin belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Diſtracted and weakned they may be, but wholly diſappointed and kept off they cannot be.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:121309:88"/>
            <p>The <hi>Uſe</hi> followes. And it may ſerve,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To let us ſee what to expect from the prayers of too many among us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe birds without wings, and meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers without feet, good for nothing at all. Divide us into four ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi> Prophane, Civil, Formal and penitent: We find the firſt ſort pray not at all; the ſecond, repeat a prayer; the third ſort make a prayer; but the laſt ſort only pray in Faith and power. The prayers of unrighteous perſons are little worth; <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundunt opera ſermonem;</hi> their works con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute their words, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith <hi>Hierom.</hi> And as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſpeaks of ſome words of <hi>Tiberius, Preclara verba,</hi> &amp;c. They are good words, but not ſutable to him; and the reaſon he gives, is, becauſe, <hi>ad haec caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra non conveniunt;</hi> his other words and actions are not of the ſame ſtamp. This we may read in many Scriptures, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.15. <hi>When you make many prayers, I will not he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, your hands are full of blood</hi> Jer. 7.9.16. <hi>Will ye ſteal, murther,</hi> &amp;c. and come before me? <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.10, 11, 12. See the place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> What you muſt do that you may be powerful and effectuall in prayer, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Get this qualification, be <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:121309:88"/> men:</hi> You muſt lay aſide all your ſins, not for a time only, as 'tis ſaid of the ſnake, that ſhe laies aſide her poyſon whilſt ſhe drinketh. Or as the <hi>Perſians,</hi> who kill all their venomous creatures one day in the year, and after that, ſuffer them to ſwarm as before, nor blot out the old ſcore, to begin a new one; as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh of <hi>France,</hi> that when he had done evil, he would kiſſe his crucifix, and then God and he were good friends, as he thought, and ſo might go to his old work again; but for ever, in deſire and endeavour. <hi>Is not this the faſt that I have choſen, to looſe the bands of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, and to undo heavy burdens, and to let the oppreſſed go free? that ye break every yoke. Is it not to deal thy bread to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry?</hi> &amp;c. Iſa. 58.7.55.7. <hi>Let the wicked forſake his way,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Then ſhall thy light break forth as the morning,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Then thou ſhalt call and the Lord ſhall anſwer, thou ſhalt cry, and he ſhall ſay, here I am.</hi> Your ſtubbornneſſe and pride muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, or elſe never hope to ſpeed; all your time and ſtrength is ſpent in vain. <hi>When you ſpread forth your hands to me, I will not hear, I will hide mine eies from you</hi> (while) <hi>your hands are full of blood.</hi> Sin
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:121309:89"/> is a devil in the air to hinder the aſcending of prayer; a thick cloud to ſtop the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of mercy. That which was noted of <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſar,</hi> may be here applied; when one that was up in Arms againſt him, yet at the ſame time ſent him a Crown; <hi>Coeſar</hi> ſends back the Crown with this meſſage, <hi>Let him return to his obedience, and then the Crown may be accepted.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly whatever means we uſe to obtain favour, and prevail with God, remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our ſins, had we Crowns to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to his honour, all would be in vain; Then turn from ſin. 2. <hi>You muſt pray in a time, while he will be found,</hi> Iſa. 55.6. <hi>and call upon him while he is neer.</hi> In gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you peace and liberty in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, while the Spirit ſtrives lovingly, and the Angel moves the water. God cals, waits, Grace is diſpenſed, the door is open; whilſt the day continues, a time may come, when he may not be found; a black night may come, and hide his gracious preſence, the Sun and the Stars may be turned into blood. Loſe not opportunity; be gathering <hi>Manna,</hi> whilſt it fals; call upon him: Say, his own beauty, mercy, goodneſſe moved you.</p>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:121309:89"/>
            <p>Where theſe are joined, there is a promiſe of good ſucceſſe: they neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet failed; this better deſerves then any, an affix of <hi>probatum eſt ſaepiſſimè.</hi> 1. When they are join'd in Perſons, ſo that the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner be penitent, and the penitent a petitioner; ſuch as ſee their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctingly and diſtinctly, ſuch as bewail, and flie to the <hi>fountain opened for ſin and for uncleanneſſe,</hi> may run and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d comfort, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.22. <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> 15.7. A penitents prayer doth preſuppoſe a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, though not alwaies in particular, yet alwaies in general, which is ſufficient. 2. When they are general in a Nation, when thoſe that ſit in the throne, as ſtars in the ſuperiour Orb, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the way, and give light and influence, in the power of godlineſſe, ſplendour of grace, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious performances: to deny themſelves in all hurtful vanities, and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y fervently, as did <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.3, &amp;c. When there is a Court-reformation, and a Country-reformation; when young and old, in City, Church, and State, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and cry fervently to God; when all join in acting as well as in ſpeaking of repentance; when men ſee and leave their whoring, ſwearing, exceſſive drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, their covetouſneſſe, idleneſſe, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:121309:90"/> and conformity to <hi>this world;</hi> when women leave their pride and <hi>vain-talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp;c. when both bring forth fruit meet for repentance, and walk in that humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſoundneſſe, as is moſt comely for the Goſpel, then expect good ſucceſſe from <hi>prayer,</hi> and religious drawing nigh to God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> But when will this be? It is a thing hath been long expected, ſpoken of, exhorted to by all ſorts, both <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> and others, but yet to be acted?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer: <hi>Firſt,</hi> So much is this time<note n="*" place="margin">A ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn day of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, 1657.</note> ſolemnly profeſſed, and this day invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto; <hi>viz.</hi> to repent and turn from our evil waie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and they muſt be groſſe hypocrites, which afterward do not join them, ſeeing they have repreſented the perſons and acted the parts of humble penitents, and profeſſed Reformiſts. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is the way; whereby thoſe that belong to God among us, may be brought in. Children of many prayers cannot periſh. Prayer and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſting, can caſt out Devils, and work mighty cures. However it fall out to others, it cannot but be ſucceſsful to your ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. You that labor to join them, ſhal not miſs a return. You ſhal have he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lth in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ckne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, plenty in penury, pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce in war; and who knoweth,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:121309:90"/> how far you may be accepted for others?</p>
            <p>Say then, What is the cauſe why your prayers with reference to your ſelves and the Nation, to this preſent ſeaſon, are no more ſucceſſeful? Is it not becauſe <hi>Firſt,</hi> Theſe things are not joined, in perſons, nor general in our Nation, as with grief we ſee and hear? It is true, we have had, and ſtill have much <hi>praying,</hi> but we have little do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; much ſpeaking to God, little or no reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among men; no wonder that ſo many pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are made and not heard, whilſt mens hands are full of blood; howle and cry, and yet rebel againſt God: pray, and yet grow worſe and worſe; thus this excellent engine of a Nation is marr'd, and proves to a people, like the Ark to the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims,</hi> provoke God to anger, and does the people more hurt. Praying without <hi>reforming,</hi> is but howling, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.14. <hi>They have not cryed unto me with their whole heart, when they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owled on their beds, they aſſembled themſelves for co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, wine and oyl, and they rebel againſt me,</hi> i. e. They conſume it on their luſt, and ſight againſt God with his own weapons; or, they aſſembled themſelves, and made no ſmall ſhew of devotion, but when the duty was over, they go to their old courſes again. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.15.58.4, 5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.9, 10.14.11, 12. Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> ſpeaks of luxurious Clerks in his time, that the grunting of hogs in the ſlye, was more pleaſing to God, then their ſinging of prayers in the Church; may warrantably be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:121309:91"/> here. To the wicked God ſaith, What haſt thou to do to take my Covenant into thy mouth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16. Such devotion is but beautiful abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Is it not becauſe ſuch as do join them for, and to the good of the Land, are ſome way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntenanced and troubled in moſt places? and can we think to prevail with God? what diſſembling is this, to ſpeak him fair to his face, both privately and publiquely, and ſtrike him in his fr ends after, with words, deeds, and neglect of them? <hi>If thou wilt take from the midſt of thee, the yoak, the putting forth of the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, (i. e.</hi> any way of diſgracing, contemning, deſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the people of God) <hi>and ſpeaking vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> (great ſins in moſt places) then call and cry, and I will anſwer, ſaith the Lord. <hi>Jobs</hi> friends dealt unkindly with him, but to him they muſt be reconciled, before they can be accepted. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> in their Apologies for Chriſtians, tell the Emperours plainly, what was the cauſe of thoſe plagues and judgements inflicted, becauſe Gods people, the poor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were perſecuted. They may be heard for you awhile, but you cannot be heard for your ſelves, nor all of us for the whole, ſo long as the beſt are proſcribed, and by mens tongues (who think they have a Law for it) ſo bitterly purſued. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Is it not becauſe of the cry of diviſion and backſliding among us, from God and one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er. 1. From God and the purity of his wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:121309:91"/> and ſervice, truths and commands! what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruity is it to cry unto God, and run from him. No wonder if he ſay, <hi>Go now to your idols, &amp;c.</hi> Is not this the ground of his dividing from our prayers? As ſmoak drives away the Bee from his Hive, ſo doth this ſin drive God from his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. 2. From one another. We are broken in <hi>minutula fruſtula,</hi> (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> in <hi>Africa</hi>) little, little pieces; little <hi>love</hi> and <hi>unity</hi> to be found; ſo ne cry out for them, but they mean by it their own wills. And how many caſt oyl inſtead of water upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lames of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Few ſtudy to be <hi>quiet,</hi> and of an healing ſpirit; ſome are for God and further <hi>reformation,</hi> that <hi>Chriſts</hi> government may be advanced, and eſtabliſhed in his own houſe, and ſeen among his peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; others are for <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> and <hi>Romiſh</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, a <hi>Samaritan</hi> Religion, to introduce and burniſh the filthy rags of the ſcarlet whore, though unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> better pretences. Some few are for truly good men; others and the moſt in number, are for wicked temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rizing for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aliſts, whoſe beſt piety is policy, and faith fantaſ e; and too many halt as neuters, till they ſee which is, that they may ſide with the ſtronge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. Now a divided mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ude, either pray not at all, or not for one thing, and one another; how can Chriſtians ſight and prevail, when they are in ſo many divided troops? If they do pray, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are ſlight, weak, and interrupted; ſome cry one thing, and ſome
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:121309:92"/> another, for the aſſembly was confuſed (<hi>Act.</hi> 19.32.) and the greater part knew not wherefore they were come together; as it was once in the Apoſtles time, is often in ours. This is the <hi>mors in olla,</hi> like to the <hi>Colliquintida</hi> that ſpoiled all the pottage; theſe turbulent waves overthrow the veſſel of prayer, and we ſee no return of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Is it not from our unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for mercies received, and ſhameful barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in improving them? Becauſe mercies have been fuel to feed our corruptions? Spiritual ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers have made the weeds of ſin to grow the faſter. Such dunghilly hearts are in mortals, that many times, the more God ſhines on us with his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, the more they putrifie; the better he is to us, have we not been the worſe to him? the more he loved us, hath he not the leſſe been loved by us? As the Ocean takes in all the freſh rivers, but is not a jot the freſher for it, ſo are we inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of what we have received; and think we not this an intolerable provocation? Unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is an helliſh ſtop to future mercies. A man that is about to pour oyl into a glaſſe, if he ſee it crackt, he ſtaies his hand and ſaith, I will pour no more oyl into this glaſſe. The unthankful heart is the broken glaſſe, not fit to receive any more bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. Unthankfulneſſe was the ſin for which God gave over the Heathens to a reprobate mind, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21, 27. It is related of the <hi>Romans</hi> that they made a law, that if a maſter did free a
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:121309:92"/> ſervant from bondage, and afterward that ſervant prove unthankful; the maſter had power to re-inſlave him. The great God hath beſtowed many mercies upon the Nation, he hath delivered us from <hi>Babylon, Egypt,</hi> and thoſe that had evil will to us: innumerable are the mercies heaped upon <hi>England;</hi> now if we prove unthankful, we may not expect otherwiſe to be dealt with, then to want an anſwer to our beſt prayers, yea, be re-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved, and brought under former hazards. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe is a ſin that makes the times peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What may be done that we may prevail more?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To what hath been already ſaid, I ſhall add here two things more, <hi>viz. Conſtancy</hi> and <hi>Regulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> 1. <hi>Conſtancy,</hi> till you have gone through the work; be not ſlight and careleſſe, nor weary in ſeeking God, as ſluggards in wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, or cowards in war. Prayer muſt be re-doubled, and re-inforced like thoſe arrows of deliverance, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 13.19. As the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> when denied, and ſhews her ſelf a woman of a well-kni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſolution. And <hi>Jacob,</hi> who holds with his hand, when his thigh is lamed; thus the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> overc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Judg.</hi> 20.18.23, 26. They go up and ask who ſhall go up to <hi>Benjamin</hi> firſt, (a very careleſs and formal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, their multitude made them preſume to ask rather Gods direction for the thing, then his lewe and preſence;) then they came again, they wept and asked him leave (which was ſomewhat
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:121309:93"/> more ſubmiſſive, and yet not enough.) Laſtly, all the people came unto the houſe of God, there they ſate and wept before the Lord, and faſted that day until evening, and offered burnt-offering, &amp;c. thus they went through the work and prevailed. As <hi>Dali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ah</hi> overcame <hi>Sampſon,</hi> ſo may we overcome God; where neither love, nor reaſon, nor deſert will gain, conſtancy will. 2. <hi>Regularity,</hi> under which I compriſe, <hi>Firſt, Order;</hi> that reformation go before your petition; firſt, amend, &amp; then pray. Reformation is the wing of the ſoul to fly hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-ward; one leg to help the ſoul to walk &amp; run to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> As a man cannot run with one leg, nor a bird fly with one wing, no more can we get to Heaven by prayer without reformation. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, nothing remains to hinder, or queſtion your entrance at the door of mercy. <hi>If you regard iniquity in your heart, the Lord will not hear.</hi> They do wel that reform though it be after; they do bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that reform &amp; pray together; but they do beſt, that lay aſide their filthy garments, before they come into Gods preſence. <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution is an excellent copy for us in this caſe to write after, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 26.6. <hi>I will waſh mine hands in innocency, and ſo will I compaſſe thine Altar, O Lord! Secondly, Rule;</hi> what you do, muſt be like good builders, who firſt lay a good foundation, and afterward aſcend by line and directions from the maſter-builder; For help <hi>herein,</hi> is the intent of the whole diſcourſe.</p>
            <trailer>Gloria Deo, mihi condonatio!</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121309:93"/>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:121309:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:121309:94"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
